<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks upon the Reflections of the author of Popery misrepresented, &amp;c. on his answerer, particularly as to the deposing doctrine in a letter to the author of the Reflections, together with some few animadversions on the same author's Vindication of his Reflections.</title>
            <author>Seller, Abednego, 1646?-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10424</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11907189</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11907189</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50742</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50742)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 511:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarks upon the Reflections of the author of Popery misrepresented, &amp;c. on his answerer, particularly as to the deposing doctrine in a letter to the author of the Reflections, together with some few animadversions on the same author's Vindication of his Reflections.</title>
                  <author>Seller, Abednego, 1646?-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 68, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Abednego Seller. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Reply to John Gother's "Reflections of the author of Popery misrepresented", and "Papists protesting against Protestant-popery ... being a vindication of the Papist misrepresented ... and the Reflexions upon the Answer."</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gother, John, d. 1704. --  Reflections upon the answer to The papist mis-represented.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:50742:1"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Z. Iſham R. P. D. Henrico Epiſc. Lond. a Sacris,</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi> April</hi> 6. 1686.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50742:1"/>
            <p>REMARKS UPON THE REFLECTIONS Of the Author of <hi>Popery Miſrepreſented,</hi> &amp;c. ON HIS ANSWERER; Particularly as to the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine.</hi> In a Letter to the AUTHOR of the <hi>Reflections.</hi> Together with ſome few <hi>Animadverſions</hi> on the ſame Author's <hi>Vindication of his Reflections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Smith</hi> at the <hi>Prince's Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1686.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body xml:lang="eng">
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50742:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50742:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not any diſtruſt of the Abilities of your former Adverſary (which have ſufficiently made him known) nor an overweening Opinion of my own undertaking, that hath engaged me in this Controverſie, but a deſign to ſerve the Intereſts of Truth, and to aſſure you, that you have not yet convinc't the World, that your Character of your Religion, as you repreſent it, is ſo juſt, and exact, or your Reaſonings ſo cogent, but there is ſomething [perhaps material, and of weight] to be objected to both; and I ſhall follow the Method, that <note n="*" place="margin">Refl. p. 1.</note> you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to like, to reaſon as cloſely, as I can, with all <hi>moderation,</hi> and <hi>calmneſs,</hi> without making any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, but ſuch as cannot be avoided, when I treat of ſome Subjects, among which, I dare undertake, none ſhall perſonally concern you; tho you will allow me to tell you, you have not ſo carefully fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed your own praeſcriptions, when you impeach our
<note n="†" place="margin">Refl. p. 2.</note> Church in general, reckoning her <hi>Books of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> among thoſe Books, that have <hi>miſrepreſented Popery;</hi> and in particular charge your learned, and modeſt Adverſary with the <note n="*" place="margin">P. 3, 4, 18.</note> ſame crime, and too liberally beſtow your Characters on him, charging him
<note n="†" place="margin">Refl. p. 6.</note> with <hi>wronging you,</hi> and <hi>impoſing upon his Reader,</hi> with <note n="*" place="margin">P. 16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Sophiſtry,</hi> with <hi>underſtanding neither Law, nor Logick,</hi> and with being <hi>inſincere,</hi> and <hi>uſing tricks,</hi> but probably the Anſwer hath made you angry, and men in a paſſion cannot forbear hard Language.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:50742:3"/>
            <p>I do acknowledge, that it is ſevere dealing to pick up all the extravagant paſſages in private Authors, and to father them on the whole Church (no Church, of whatever denomination, being without both evil men as to their Morals, and opinionative men as to their Tenets) but withal I muſt ſay, that it is one thing to cite Quotations from all ſorts of Authors, and another thing to cite Men of Eminence, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in your Church, (and ſuch, whoſe Station, Learning, and Repute, were as great, as ever the <hi>Biſhop of Condom</hi>'s, or <hi>Monſieur Veron</hi>'s, whom yet you rely upon, as you alſo ſometimes quote other men of your Communion to confirm your Opinions) whoſe Books alſo have come into the World with Licence, and Priviledge, and Commendations of the Authors, and whoſe Aſſertions have never been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, after they have been publiſht, (and ſome of them probably Members of that very <hi>Trent-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel,</hi> which you ſtick to for the Articles of your Faith) and in matters of fact, which cannot be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign to the Controverſies between your Church, and ours, there is a neceſſity of having recourſe to ſuch Writers, as I ſhall be often forc't to do in theſe <hi>Remarks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that I may conſider every thing methodical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that belongs to this <hi>Topick,</hi> I cannot but obſerve your <note n="*" place="margin">Refl. p. 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>Reflections</hi> on the Opinions of ſome Eminent men in our Communion, which, ſay you, we are unwilling to have charg'd upon our Church. For the firſt, which you charge on your Antagoniſt, <hi>That, good works of juſtified perſons are not free,</hi> I muſt ſay, that either I miſunderſtand your Adverſary, or you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50742:3"/>do <hi>miſrepreſent</hi> him; for when <note n="†" place="margin">Ch. 6. p. 43. Ed. 3.</note> he ſays, <hi>That, what we pretend to merit by, muſt be our own free act;</hi> (for theſe are his words, and not as you quote them) citing for it the Authority of the <hi>Jeſuit Coſter's En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiridion,</hi> and adds, <hi>That therefore the works of juſtified perſons cannot be ſaid to be their own free acts, becauſe the power of doing them depends upon Divine aſſiſtance; and being done by the power of God's grace, which could never have been done without it, cannot be</hi> (for that reaſon) <hi>truly meritorious,</hi> he is ſo far from giving an account of the Doctrine of our Church, that he proves from the principles of your own, that, if good works be done only by the Grace of God, and made acceptable only through the merits of Chriſt, they cannot be truly ſaid to be meritorious, becauſe not the free acts of them, that do them.</p>
            <p>When Mr. <hi>Thorndyke</hi> allows of <hi>prayers for the Dead</hi> (though you quote no Book of his for that Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion) he does no more, than in ſome ſenſe our Church allows, when it prays for a joyful Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in <hi>her Office at Funerals;</hi> and whatever the good man might add elſe of his own, was but his private Opinion (as is alſo his notion, that the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtical Sacrifice is truly the Sacrifice of Chriſt upon the Croſs propitiatory, and impetratory, as well as the other,</hi> which I take upon your credit, not having the Book by me, out of which you cite the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) however we aſſert, that Mr. <hi>Thornayke</hi> never owned <hi>Prayers for the Dead,</hi> as you do (but in the ſenſe of ſome of the Antients) for he denied <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> upon which you ground your <hi>Prayers for the Dead,</hi> and that our Bleſſed Saviour is really preſent in the Sacrament, is the Doctrine and Belief of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50742:4"/>
               <hi>Church of England,</hi> and did not you limit that <hi>Real Preſence</hi> to <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> there would be no <hi>difference</hi> between you, and us in that point.</p>
            <p>I cannot but obſerve your diſingenuous manner of treating the Author of <hi>Jovian,</hi> in charging him with a diſloyal principle, who hath given as many Inſtances of his Loyalty, in the moſt difficult times, as any man of his ſtation; and were there no other, the writing of that excellent Treatiſe, in that criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal juncture, is an undeniable evidence of it, when by defending the Succeſſion, and the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance, he acquired the ill will, and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all the diſloyal Party. Why did not you, nor any other of the Engliſh Roman Catholicks, write then in the defence of thoſe Doctrines, againſt the diſloyal and rebellious Doctrines of <hi>Julian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Preſs was open for you, and perhaps there was reaſon for your not anſwering of them,
<note n="*" place="margin">Praefat. Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm. ante tractat. de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testate ſummi Pont. adverſus G. Barclay.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the generality of the Writers of your Church agree with that Author in his principles of diſloyalty. Well, but you have found out one diſloyal principle in <hi>Jovian,</hi> but are you ſure of it? It is not your ſaying, It is a diſloyal principle, that makes it to be ſo, and therefore I muſt deſire you, and thoſe that perhaps are miſled by you, to read the Book from p. 139. to p. 152. out of which you have cited the paſſage, and then you will find it to be ſuch a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal principle, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod.</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> as will not allow any Chriſtian ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<q>[<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>]</q> to pray for the death of a <hi>Nero, Diocleſian,</hi> (though he ſet up Inſcriptions, <hi>ob deletum nomen Chriſtianum,</hi>) <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> or <hi>Valens,</hi> but only
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50742:4"/>for a <hi>Julian,</hi> whoſe Apoſtaſie and Wickedneſs is fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular in Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, and the like of whom in all probability can never be expected again.</p>
            <p>Nay Sir, this diſloyal principle will not let Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſnbjects pray, for the death of a <hi>Julian,</hi> though he tyranizes never ſo much over their bodies, goods and liberties, if he do not blaſpheme Chriſt, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Church of God, with a diabolical ſpite, againſt the evidence of Divine Miracles. It leaves the Chriſtian ſubjects of all Tyrants, but ſuch as are <hi>Julians indeed,</hi> under the obligation of praying for them, according to the Apoſtle's direction, and the practice of the Primitive Chriſtians, which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>Jovian</hi> hath ſo much inſiſted upon, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended; and his Prince muſt be a <hi>Julian indeed,</hi> a <hi>Julian</hi> in all circumſtances, before he can be ſo much as tempted to pray againſt him; for he doth not ſay, that he would pray, but that he ſhould be tempted to pray for the deſtruction of a <hi>Julian indeed.</hi> And it had been happy for the Chriſtian world, if the chief Paſtors, and Biſhops, and Councils, and Doctors, and Caſuiſts, of that which you call the Catholick Church, had never taught any principle more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal than this. Now Sir, I beſeech you, to tell me, how much diſloyalty there is in this principle, which ſecures all Infidel, Heretical, and Apoſtate Princes againſt the Prayers of their Chriſtian ſubjects, unleſs they be in all degrees as bad as <hi>Julian,</hi> and ſecures even <hi>Julians</hi> themſelves againſt all reſiſtance? and how much diſloyalty there is in a man, who by his principles will pray for all Tyrants, but ſuch an one as <hi>Julian</hi> was, according to the Author of <hi>Jovian?</hi> Sir I would to God you, and your Doctors would
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50742:5"/>declare as much Loyalty as this; and I deſire you to tell me, that ſuppoſe a Roman Catholick Prince ſhould become a <hi>Julian indeed,</hi> and take up the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of that Apoſtate, whether you think his Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Subjects would be tempted to pray for his deſtruction? and if they ſhould do ſo and no more, do you think they would tranſgreſs any rule of Chriſtian Loyalty? Anſwer me theſe two queſtions ſincerely and poſſitively; and if your anſwer to the laſt, be affirmative, give your arguments for your O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and I dare engage, the Author of <hi>Jovian</hi> ſhall ſubmit to your reaſons, or anſwer them.</p>
            <p>For I am confident he hath no fondneſs for his Opinion, to which it is evident he was led, by his great Charity for the Biſhop, and Church of <hi>Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzum.</hi> And though in apologizing for them, he hath aſſerted, that he ſhould be tempted to pray for the deſtruction of a <hi>Julian indeed,</hi> yet he is ſo Loyal a Perſon, that I believe he would overcome the temptation, and only forbear praying for him, as having ſinned the ſin unto death.</p>
            <p>After which Apology you will ſuffer me to tell you, that your <hi>Reflections</hi> will hardly be called an anſwer to <hi>the Doctrines, and Practices of the Church of Rome,</hi> becauſe in them you have not ſaid a word to ſome <hi>material points</hi> of Controverſy between you, and us, ſtated in that Book out of the <hi>Trent-Council</hi> and <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> as if either the right were on your Adverſaries ſide [which, I ſuppoſe, you will be loath to acknowledge] or his reaſonings were unworthy your ſecond thoughts [which, I ſuppoſe, you will not own, and if you do, few wiſe men will acquieſce
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50742:5"/>in your Sentiments] for you wholly praetermit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon the Chapters of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> of <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences,</hi> of <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> ex condigno, of <hi>keeping the Scriptures, and Prayers in an unknown Tongue,</hi> of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in one kind,</hi> and of <hi>adding the Apocrypha,</hi> and <hi>traditions to the holy writ,</hi> with ſome others; which, being ſome of the <hi>moſt material points</hi> in difference between your Church, and ours, will either deſerve ſome new thoughts, or you will allow us to ſay, that that book cannot be thought an anſwer, which in ſilence paſſes by, or leaps over ſo many weighty things, that make up ſo much of the Controverſy.</p>
            <p>You aſſure us, <note n="*" place="margin">Refl. p. 5.</note> 
               <hi>that the Council of</hi> Trent <hi>is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved here, and all the Catholick World over as to its defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Faith, though it be not wholly received in ſome places as to its other decrees, which relate only to diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi> Where I ſhall not ask, what you mean by the <hi>Catholick World,</hi> for I am well aſſured that you mean all Chriſtians of the <hi>Roman</hi> perſuaſion, which is a very narrow notion of the <hi>Catholick World,</hi> exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all other Chriſtians from being Members of the Catholick Church, but thoſe of your own Opinion; ſo that neither the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, nor the reſt of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Chriſtians are in your ſenſe any more Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, than the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (though antiently any man, or Church of men, were called <hi>Catholick,</hi> becauſe they agreed with the whole <hi>Catholick Church</hi> in Faith; but now the <hi>holy Catholick Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt loſe its name, if it agree not with the particular Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) but I would willingly know of you, whence any particular Church hath that power, that it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a <hi>general Council</hi> (as you call that of <hi>Trent</hi>) in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50742:6"/>ſome things, and not in others? I thought, that the higheſt authority of the Church on Earth had been a <hi>general Council,</hi> and if ſo, why its definitions in matters of diſcipline ſhould not be received and obſerved by all particular Churches, is to me a great queſtion; for I cannot but ſee, that one of theſe two things muſt follow from your Opinion, either that <hi>Councils</hi> and <hi>Popes</hi> are fallible (for if they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in one Opinion, ſuch as that of the power of the Church to <hi>depoſe Princes,</hi> why may they not be deceived in another, ſuch as <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> or <hi>Purgatory?</hi>) or elſe, that they are infallible in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matters only, and then to me it is a great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that they ſhould erre in things of leſs moment; and I never yet underſtood, but that if <hi>general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils</hi> could decide matters of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> but that they had alſo as great a power in matters of <hi>diſcipline</hi> (for if it be a lawful preface to the decrees of all <hi>Councils,</hi> as your men ſay, <hi>Viſum eſt ſpiritui ſancto, &amp; nobis,</hi> then the <hi>holy ſpirit</hi> is doubtleſs their guide in matters of <hi>diſcipline,</hi> as well as in matters of <hi>Doctrine.</hi>) I am ſure, that the <hi>Antient Councils</hi> took upon them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide both by their authority, and all Chriſtians thought themſelves oblig'd to follow their dictates; ſo the <hi>firſt general Council of the Apoſtles</hi> bound up all Chriſtians from <hi>eating things ſtrangled, and Blood;</hi> ſo the <hi>Council of Nice</hi> determin'd the preciſe day, when <hi>Eaſter</hi> ſhould be celebrated, as well as the <hi>Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiality of the Son with the Father;</hi> and ſo alſo the <hi>ſecond general Council</hi> made <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> a <hi>Patriarchate</hi> as well as <hi>Rome;</hi> to go no further. And I find no perſons diſputed thoſe conſtitutions (though only in matters of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>Government</hi>) till the <hi>Popes</hi> began to aſſert their Authority in oppoſition to <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Councils.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50742:6"/>
            <p>And whereas <note n="*" place="margin">Refl. p. 6.</note> you ſay, that your Adverſary <hi>wrongs you,</hi> and <hi>impoſes upon his Reader,</hi> by ſaying, that <hi>you give your private ſenſe, and Opinion only of the Articles of your Religion contrary to the Bull of</hi> Pius 4. pleading in your own behalf, <hi>that you expound the Canons of the</hi> Trent-<hi>Council according to the Catechiſm ſet forth by the order of the Council, and the Pope,</hi> as if both of them allowed of it; I muſt ſay, that this cannot be, for the <hi>Council</hi> never ſaw the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> and conſequently could never approve, that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw, unleſs they alſo were bound to exerciſe an implicite Faith; for though they ordered a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſſ,</hi> 18. <hi>&amp; Seſſ.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <hi>Catechiſm</hi> to be publiſht (having obſerv'd, how much the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> prevailed againſt their Church by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Catechizing</hi>) they left it wholly to the <hi>Pope</hi> to ſee it done, and to give it authority; and this the Author of the <hi>Prolegomena</hi> to the <hi>Paris Edition</hi> of that <hi>Catechiſm, An.</hi> 1671. fairly acknowledges <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Proleg.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.</note>, affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that after the diſſolution of the <hi>Council, An.</hi> 1563. ſeveral Fathers were ſummon'd to <hi>Rome</hi> to make this <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> among whom the principal man was <hi>S. Barromée</hi> (as you call him) <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Millan;</hi> we are alſo told, that <hi>Cardinal Seripandus</hi> made the explanation of that Article <hi>(one holy Catholick Church) Michael Medina</hi> of another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that after it was finiſht, it was <hi>An.</hi> 1566. offered to <hi>Pope Pius</hi> 5. for his approbation, who committed the examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it to <hi>Cardinal Sirlet,</hi> who taking to himſelf the aſſiſtance of other learned men, examined both the matter, and language of it, after which the <hi>Pope</hi> gave his approbation, and ordered it to be printed by <hi>Paulus Manutius,</hi> confirming it by his <hi>Bulls.</hi> And <hi>Poſſevine</hi> tells us, that <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13. made this <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm</hi> the rule, by which he reformed the <hi>Canon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50742:7"/>Law;</hi> ſo that if <note place="margin">Refl. p. 6.</note> you <hi>interpret the Canons of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil by the Catechiſm,</hi> then the <hi>Canons</hi> depend upon the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> for their meaning, and the ſenſe of the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> upon the <hi>Pope,</hi> who gave it suthority, by which deduction it appears, that your Rengion is ſtill built not on the <hi>Council,</hi> but on the <hi>Pope;</hi> and perhaps it was for this reaſon, that the <hi>Italian Biſhops</hi> in their <hi>Synods</hi> (as do the <hi>Synods</hi> of <hi>Roven,</hi> and <hi>Aix</hi> in <hi>France</hi>) call it not the <hi>Trent,</hi> but the <hi>Roman Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm,</hi> for in truth ſo it is. Againſt all which I know only this to be objected, that the ſame men, that made the <hi>Canons,</hi> made the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> (which is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true, as to every particular perſon) but to that I anſwer, that I believe, you will not averr; that the ſame men have the ſame aſſiſtances in a <hi>Council,</hi> and out of it; ſo that were the aſſertion true, yet the one being done in <hi>Council,</hi> had the aſſiſtance of the Bleſſed Spirit (as you hold) to aſſiſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilers; which, I preſume, you will not ſay, that the ſame men had, when out of the <hi>Council.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this be ſo, then does not this make the <hi>Pope</hi> judge of Controverſies of <hi>Faith?</hi> For, ſay you, <hi>the Church muſt interpret Scripture, and interpret Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith declared in Councils,</hi> which Church muſt either be the <hi>Church Repreſentative,</hi> or the <hi>Pope;</hi> now to hope for a <hi>general Council</hi> upon every emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent diſpute in matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> is a vain exſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and if ſo, you will do well to ſhow us any other judge in ſuch caſes, but the <hi>Pope;</hi> unleſs every particular Church muſt judge for it ſelf, or every private perſon be his own director, and then, where is the interpretation of the <hi>Church Catholick?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:50742:7"/>
            <p>Now if the <hi>Pope</hi> be the Judge, how know we, but the next <hi>Pope</hi> may require the belief of the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine,</hi> and expound the paſſages of former <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils</hi> that look that way, as Articles of <hi>Faith?</hi> what would you do in that caſe, eſpecially if the generality of the <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> ſhould ſide with him
[as they did in the caſe of the <hi>Emperour Henry</hi> 4. and of our <hi>King John</hi>] and in their <hi>Synods</hi> declare for the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Monarchy?</hi> — and upon this ſuppoſition, how know we, but that, although the preſent <hi>Pope</hi> hath confirm'd the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Book, another <hi>Pope</hi> may condemn his mincing the Articles of Faith? for we do not want Inſtances of <hi>Popes,</hi> who have reſcinded, not only one anothers <hi>Acts,</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinations,</hi> but one anothers <hi>Decrees,</hi> even in what they have called <hi>matters of Faith;</hi> although I muſt confeſs, what is very obſervable, that though very many <hi>Popes</hi> have aſſerted the Eccleſiaſtical Power over Princes, and their <hi>Right of Depoſing</hi> them, we never read of one of them, that condemned the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>You further ſay, <note n="*" place="margin">Refl. p. 7.</note> that though the <hi>Trent Council mention the Aid, and Aſſiſtance of the Saints, and Angels over and above their Prayers, yet it means no other Aid, but that of their Prayers,</hi> which ſeem to me not ſo agreeable to the words of the <hi>Council</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Seſſ. 25.</note>, which are, <hi>That it is good, and uſeful ad ſanctorum orationes, opem, auxiliumque confugere, to fly to their Prayers, Aid, and Aſſiſtance.</hi> Now I cannot believe, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of that <hi>Council</hi> would have explain'd a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular act by two more general words, nor when they had mention'd in particular, <hi>Prayers,</hi> would they, I believe, have afterward inſerted in general
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50742:8"/>their <hi>Aid,</hi> and <hi>Aſſiſtances,</hi> unleſs the <hi>Aid,</hi> and <hi>Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> were diſtinct from their <hi>Interceſſion;</hi> and this is agreeable to your allowed Prayers in your <hi>Miſſal,</hi> where you beg God,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dec.</hi> 6. <hi>in fest. S. Nicol.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ut ejus meritis, &amp; precibus, &amp;c. that by the merits, and prayers of St.</hi> Nicolas, <hi>you may be deliver'd from the flames of Hell.</hi> And again, <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jul.</hi> 6. <hi>Octav. SS. Petri, &amp; Pauli.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That by the merits of St.</hi> Peter, <hi>and St.</hi> Paul, <hi>you may attain the glories of Eternity,</hi> where the <hi>Merits,</hi> and <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions</hi> of <hi>the Saints</hi> are manifeſtly diſtinguiſht, as they are alſo in the <hi>Trent-Catechiſm,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>praecept.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 24.</note> where in the Margin there is this Note, <hi>The Saints help us with their Merits;</hi> and in the body of the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> theſe; <hi>They always pray for the happineſs of men, and God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers many benefits upon us, eorum merito, &amp; gratiâ, for their merits, and ſake;</hi> and truly, were we aſſured that the Guardian Angels could hear us, I ſee no reaſon why we ſhould ſcruple any more to pray them to protect us againſt the Devil, and all other Enemies that may hurt us, than to beg them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercede for us to God; and this alſo is agreeable to the <hi>Catechiſm</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſupr. n.</hi> 18.</note>.</p>
            <p>Your next <hi>Reflection</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">p. 8.</note> is about the <hi>merit of good works,</hi> and your ſelf, and adverſary are agreed, that <hi>Can.</hi> 32. <hi>Seſſ. 6.</hi> of the <hi>Council of Trent</hi> there is no mention of the qualification of <hi>Merit</hi> with reſpect to dependance on God's grace, goodneſs, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; but both in that <hi>Canon,</hi> and <hi>Can.</hi> 26. the words are plain, <hi>quae ab eo per Dei gratiam (miſericordiam) &amp; Jeſu Chriſti meritum, &amp;c.</hi> And if ſo, the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie ſeems to me eaſily decided; <hi>for if it be of grace, how is it then of works?</hi> where is the merit?</p>
            <p>Your Anſwer to the <hi>Goliah Argument</hi> of your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, as you are pleaſed to call it, I remit to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50742:8"/>conſider'd towards the end of theſe <hi>Remarks,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ought to be ſpoken to more largely, and by it ſelf, and proceed to take notice, that
<note n="*" place="margin">Refl. p. 11.</note> you blame your Adverſary for <hi>taking the ſenſe of your Church from ſome expreſſions in your old Miſſals, and Rituals,</hi>
[tho I am apt to think, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> will be contented to be judged by her <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals</hi> in the like caſe] but perhaps you are not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſted at the uſe of your <hi>Miſſals,</hi> but at the uſe of <hi>old Miſſals;</hi> and I am perſuaded, that you have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo to be, becauſe the ſubtilty of the modern Church hath made it ſelf appear in your preſent <hi>Miſſals,</hi> and <hi>Breviaries,</hi> as well as in your Edition of the <hi>Vulgar Tranſlation</hi> of <hi>the Bible,</hi> and in other Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes. For inſtance, in the old <hi>Roman Breviary</hi> print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Venice An.</hi> 1482. and at <hi>Paris An.</hi> 1543. <hi>Jun.</hi> 28. <hi>lect.</hi> 2. <hi>noct.</hi> 2. <hi>S. Leonis,</hi> the words run thus, <hi>In eo Concilio damnati ſunt Cyrus, &amp; Sergius, Honorius, Pyrrhus, Paulus, &amp;c.</hi> in <hi>that Synod Cyrus,</hi> and <hi>Sergius, Honorius,</hi> &amp;c, <hi>were condemned;</hi> but in the new <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viary</hi> the name of <hi>Honorius</hi> is left out, which, had it been left there, would have reflected too much on the <hi>Papal Infallibility,</hi> and inform'd the World, that even <hi>Popes</hi> themſelves have fallen into Hereſie; while in the ſame Office they take care to keep up the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, that that <hi>Pope Leo</hi> 2. <hi>fregit ſuperbiam Ravenna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, brought the Archbiſhop of</hi> Ravenna <hi>to acknowledge the</hi> Roman <hi>Supremacy, which before that time that See did not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond Inſtance may be this: In all the <hi>antient Miſſals</hi> in <hi>Cathedra, S. Petri Antioch, Feb.</hi> 22. (as alſo in the old <hi>Diumale</hi> printed at <hi>Antwerp</hi> 1553.) the Prayer is read in theſe words, <hi>Deus qui B. Petro Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50742:9"/>collatis clavibus regni coeleſtis animas ligandi, atque ſolvendi pontificium dediſti,</hi> i. e. <hi>O God, who having given thy bleſſed Apoſtle St.</hi> Peter <hi>the Keys of thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdom, gaveſt him Epiſcopal power of binding, and looſing Souls;</hi> but they have now left out the word <hi>Animas, i. e.</hi> Souls; for with that limitation the <hi>Pope</hi>'s power was only Prieſtly to uſe the Keys <hi>in binding,</hi> and <hi>looſing men's Souls,</hi> but without that limitation every man is at liberty to believe that St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Keys may be imployed in temporal affairs alſo, in <hi>binding Kings,</hi> and ſetting up a <hi>Pontifical Monarchy,</hi> to which I ſhall add one Inſtance more; that whereas in the <hi>Sacramentarium</hi> of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Prayer for St. <hi>Leo</hi> runs thus, <hi>Annue nobis, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp;c. Grant, O Lord, that this Oblation may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to the Soul of thy Servant</hi> Leo; now the words are altered into, <hi>Annue, &amp;c. Grant, Lord, that by the interceſſion of thy Servant</hi> Leo, <hi>this Oblation may be profitable to us;</hi> the firſt being an Inſtance of the Antients Prayers for the Dead, for Saints, as well as others; the latter an endeavour to countenance Prayers to Saints by aſſerting their interceſſion.</p>
            <p>And whereas to requite us for quoting your <hi>Miſſals</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>, you object to us all the <hi>expreſſions of Prayer, Preaching, and Devotion in our Church,</hi> the parallel doth not hold, unleſs you mean our authoriz'd <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy,</hi> in whoſe collects we are ready to vindicate, whatever is aſſerted. Nor is it fair to ſay, <hi>that an Atheiſt may make himſelf ſport with Scripture, if he may be allowed to ſeparate an infinite number of expreſſions there, i. e.</hi> as I underſtand you, to make uſe of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſentences (for if an Atheiſt uſes Scripture in the ſenſe, to which the coherence leads him, he can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50742:9"/>make <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> ridiculous, much leſs <hi>as ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as Turciſm</hi>) and for the paſſages quoted out of your <hi>Miſſals,</hi> they are quoted in the ſenſe, in which they are meant, and if you deny this, you may right your ſelf by ſhewing the contrary.</p>
            <p>Nor do you do well with the Church of <hi>England</hi> to ſay, <note n="*" place="margin">Refl. p. 11.</note> ſhe <hi>allows the Pſalms in Meeter.</hi> I dare be confident to averr, that the <hi>Singing Pſalms</hi> (as they are uſally called) were never commanded by our Church to be uſed, and are no part of our ſervice, as our <hi>Rubric</hi>'s will inform you, where there is not the leſt mention of them; though we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the cuſtom was brought in through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance of our Governors, who at that time were intent upon matters of greater moment; nor do we ſay, <hi>that the ſenſe of the Church will help out the non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, or ill expreſſions of any of thoſe Rhymes</hi> (which is a ſubtle inſinuation) but withal we ſay, that ſince cuſtom hath brought in the uſe, no Prieſt of our Communion, that I know of, is ſo weak (I am ſure, no one ought to be ſo) but he knows how to chooſe out of that great number ſome few Pſalms, that are pertinently enough tranſlated, and incentive of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, by ſinging of which neither God is diſhonor'd, nor the Congregation engaged to any thing, that is either evil, or ridiculous; which Apology cannot be made for any of your <hi>Miſſals,</hi> which your Prieſts were obliged to uſe without any power left them to chooſe what <hi>Collects,</hi> or <hi>Antiphona</hi>'s, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they pleaſed.</p>
            <p>And now you will allow me to ſmile, when <note n="†" place="margin">Refl. p. 12.</note> you ſay, <hi>that if we conclude a Papiſt guilty of Idolatry, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he bows down, kneels,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to an Image, we may
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50742:10"/>as well ſay, that</hi> Abigail <hi>was guilty of conſtructive Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, when ſhe fell on her face before</hi> David, <hi>and ſo are Subjects, when they kneel to their Prince, and the</hi> Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colns-Inn-Field <hi>Beggars, when they kneel for an Alms to thoſe, who paſs by.</hi> For theſe inſtances do not reach the caſe, that we are talking of; for if <hi>Abigail</hi> ſhould have kneel'd before the Picture of <hi>David,</hi> or a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject before the Picture of his Prince, or a Beggar be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Gentleman's Picture, and begg'd with earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſeeming devotion any bleſſing, there is no ſober man, but would believe, that they were either very mad, or very fooliſh; but if they thought them ſober, and in their right ſenſe, (as we do believe your people at Church to be) they cannot be acquitted of Idolatry, if ſo be the honour be Religious (as you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, your veneration of Images is more than civil honour) ſo that by theſe inſtances you ſeem to run into the errour of thoſe <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Alenſ. Aq. Bonav. &amp;c. apud Bellar. to.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c</hi> 20. § 2. <hi>Opinio.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> that the ſame honour (let it be <hi>Latria, hyperdulia,</hi> or <hi>dulia</hi>) is due to the Image, that is, due to the perſon repreſented; and if any Law be to be judg'd of by the common practice (as the Maxim faith, <hi>Lex currit cum praxi</hi>) this is very plain from the uſages of the generality of people in your Church. And I am ſure, (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this your way of arguing) that I have ſomewhere read (though I cannot now readily light on the place) that <hi>Scribanius</hi> affirms, that <hi>Adoration of Saints, and Images</hi> is very lawful, becauſe <hi>Abraham bowed down to the Children of</hi> Heth, Gen. 23.7. <hi>Surrexit Abraham, &amp; adoravit populum terrae, filios,</hi> viz. <hi>Heth.</hi> As it is in the <hi>Vulgar Latine.</hi> And if I muſt not judge of any man's Idolatry <hi>by his outward actions</hi> (which is your excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) then I can never know any man to be an <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> for a Heathen may fall down before one of his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50742:10"/>Idols, and call upon it for help, and yet ſay, that his intention is juſt, and that he only meant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to worſhip the True God, which is the excuſe made by the men of your Church.</p>
            <p>After this, <note n="*" place="margin">Refl. p. 16.</note> you compare the <hi>Power of the Pope to that of Civil Powers, as to the Obedience due to them from their Subjects;</hi> but, pray deal candidly, Do you believe the <hi>Pope</hi> to have no more Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in commanding Obedience, than Civil Powers have? Doubtleſs you do believe him to have more Authority, or elſe, why do ſo many of your Church refuſe to take the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> which yet you
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cath. princ. ſect.</hi> 2. § 4. <hi>p.</hi> 3.</note> allow to be a lawful Oath? for you ſay, they refuſe it, <hi>not for any unlawfulneſs in the Oath, but becauſe the Doctrine of Depoſing Princes is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in called Heretical, which they cannot allow of, as the word is underſtood in a Catholick ſenſe</hi> (where you will allow me to obſerve, that for the true notion of Hereſie, you depend on the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>Breve,</hi> and ſo allow the <hi>Pope</hi> to be a Judge in matters of <hi>Faith;</hi> for Hereſie is contrary to the <hi>Faith,</hi> and conſequently the <hi>Depoſing Power,</hi> which the <hi>Pope</hi> hath determin'd, is a matter of <hi>Faith</hi>) and why do they follow the <hi>Papal</hi> Dictates in thoſe things, wherein by the Laws of God, and Nations they are bound to ſubmit to their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours?</p>
            <p>Here alſo I obſerve, that when <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Popery miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented, p.</hi> 46.</note> you Treat of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Power, you give your ſelf a great lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, when you ſay, That <hi>you never ſcruple to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Decrees, and Definitions, ſuch as are iſſued forth by his Authority, with all their due Circumſtances,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50742:11"/>and according to Law;</hi> but never tell us, what thoſe <hi>Circumſtances</hi> are (as your Adverſary well remarks) which puts me in <hi>mind</hi> of ſomewhat, which <hi>your <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tanner diſp.</hi> 1. <hi>de fid. q.</hi> 4. <hi>dub.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 263. <hi>Compton. in</hi> 22. <hi>diſ.</hi> 22. § 5.</note> Authors</hi> ſay concerning the <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. prefixt to his Edition of the <hi>Vulgar Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> which was afterward recalled by <hi>Clement</hi> 8. <hi>That it was true the Bull was printed with the Bible, but that it was not affixt to the Gates of St.</hi> Peter<hi>'s Church, and in the</hi> Campo fiore <hi>ſo long, as it ought to have been according to the Laws of the Romiſh Chancery,</hi> as if ſuch little things as thoſe made Eccleſiaſtical Decrees more, or leſs valid.</p>
            <p>And now to ſhew you, that your <hi>Anſwerer</hi> did not ſhow his Learnlng in diſcovering, that the <hi>Popes have diſpenc't only with poſitive Inſtitutions, but not with the Moral Law, with Lying,</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing,</hi> (as if he ſought a knot in a Bull-ruſh, and <hi>took Sanctuary in a Myſtery,</hi> as you term it, by talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only in general terms) what think you of the many Diſpenſations, that have been given by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Popes</hi> to the Subjects of this, and other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, to break their <hi>Oaths of Allegiance,</hi> and Duty to their Soveraigns? (the relation between Princes, and their Subjects, being not grounded on their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but on the Obligation of <hi>Civil So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,</hi> ſo that a diſpenſing with the <hi>Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> is a diſpenſing with a Duty of Natural Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which binds Subjects to obey their Superiours.) For either Subjection to Princes is a Duty of the Fifth Commandment, (as we reckon them) <hi>Honour thy Father, and Mother,</hi> &amp;c. or it is not; if it be not, you will do well to aſſert it, and we ſhall take care to prove it to be a Duty of that Commandment, not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50742:11"/>only from the Authority of the Antients, and from Reaſon, but from the Authority of your own <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm,</hi> which <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>praec.</hi> 4. § 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.2. § 17, 18.</note> ſays, <hi>That all perſons, who are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of power, or dignity, are included under the term Parents,</hi> which is afterward explain'd by <hi>thoſe, who have Empire, Magiſtracy, or power committed to them, who govern the Commonwealth.</hi> But if to obey Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be a duty of that Commandment, then to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with that duty, is to <hi>diſpence with a Moral Law,</hi> and to diſpence with Oaths, that bind to that duty, is to give men a diſpenſation to be perjur'd, and to forſwear themſelves. And becauſe you tell us <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pap. reprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. p.</hi> 47, 48.</note>, <hi>That the Papiſt is taught in all Books, that to Lye is a ſin, and to call God to witneſs to an untruth, is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and that the practices of your Church are accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe praeſcriptions, and that neither the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor an Oath of Secrecy can excuſe any man from perjury; nor did you ever hear of any ſuch thing from any Prieſts in Sermons, or Confeſſions, never read of them in your Books, or Catechiſms, nor ſaw the practice of any of them in any of your Communion;</hi>) in which words there is ſome Art uſed; for, do you believe, that any Prieſt of your Communion may reveal what he hears in confeſſion againſt the Laws of your Church, which bind him to Secrecy <hi>ſub ſigillo?</hi> and when you tell us, <hi>You never read of any ſuch thing either in Books, or Catechiſms,</hi> you mean, I ſuppoſe, Books of Devotion; for in other Books, you may undoubtedly read ſuch Doctrines, or elſe why ſhould the <hi>Pope</hi> condemn them? And when you ſay, <hi>You never ſaw any ſuch thing,</hi> I hope you mean, it never fell within the reach of your particular obſervation; but if you read the account of Mr. <hi>Garnet,</hi> and his accomplices, you will find, that they took the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50742:12"/>as an Oath of Secrecy, to carry on that Helliſh deſign.) And withal ſubjoyn, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. p.</hi> 66.</note> 
               <hi>That the preſent Pope hath condemn'd all Equivocations, and Mental Reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions under the penalty of Excommunication</hi> latae ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae <hi>by his Decree</hi> March 2. 1679. We do ſtill averr, that your Church hath given diſpenſations for Lying, and Forſwearing, and we know not, but it may be done for the future. For, not to inſtance in the <hi>Jeſuite Moraliſts <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Filiut. to.</hi> 2. <hi>tr.</hi> 25. <hi>n.</hi> 325. <hi>Sanches oper. moral. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>n.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.</note>, Filiutius, Sanches,</hi> &amp;c. their averring, <hi>That if a man promiſes any thing, and ſwears to it, yet if he do not intend it, he may without ſin break that promiſe, and that Oath;</hi> ſo that the intention of the Swearer among theſe <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> makes the Oath valid, as the intention of the Prieſt makes the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Some other of the <hi>ſame Order,</hi> have given diſpenſations for the breach of the Moral Law <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theol. mor. to.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 7 <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>n.</hi> 281, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>; <hi>Eſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar</hi> ſays poſitively, <hi>virtute bullae poteſt votum non pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi mutari,</hi> i. e. <hi>that a man may break his Vow of not ſinning by virtue of a Bull,</hi> and he inſtances in the committing of <hi>Fornication;</hi> he <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tr.</hi> 7. <hi>ex.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 118.</note> alſo ſays, That a man may Lye even to his Confeſſor, that <hi>a man may promiſe a general Confeſſion, and yet not confeſs all his mortal ſins,</hi> quia quamvis mentiatur, id tamen parum refert ad Confeſſarii judicium, i. e. <hi>for tho he Lye, yet that hath little or no relation to the Judgment of his Confeſſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to theſe proofs probably you will object, that this is not the Opinion of the Church, but of private men; to which I anſwer, that had it not been the Opinion of your Church, when thoſe Books were written, ſuch men would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have been allowed to be <hi>Confeſſors</hi> (which no man can be unleſs by the allowance of the <hi>Pope,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50742:12"/>the Biſhop of the Dioceſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) though it is well known, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> then were, and ſtill are as Eminent for being <hi>Confeſſors,</hi> as any other Order in your Communion, and perhaps more, and this notwithſtanding their owning theſe <hi>damnable Doctrines,</hi> as both you, and I agree to call them. Nor is it enough to ſay, that the Book of <hi>Eſcobar,</hi> after having been 39 times prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for an excellent Book (which is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it was much bought, and much valued) was the 40th time printed only to be cenſured, and condemn'd by the <hi>French</hi> Biſhops (which the poor <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> lookt upon to have been a condemnation both of the Author, and his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, whereas they found at laſt to their coſt, that themſelves were cenſured at <hi>Rome,</hi> as the criminals) nor that the preſent <hi>Pope</hi> (being more wiſe, and moderate than ſome of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors) hath condemnd thoſe Doctrines (which vindicates us, that we have not unjuſtly charg'd the men of your Church with ſuch Doctrines) among which propoſitions if you conſult the 26 and 27, it is aſſerted, <hi>That a man may either, being askt, or of his own accord ſay, and ſwear, that he did not do a thing, which he really did, and yet by vertue of a ſecret meaning, be neither a lyar, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured. And that this he may do, as often as it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, or profitable to ſave his Body, Honour, or Eſtate, or for any other good end.</hi> For this is to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that your Church for a long time heretofore conniv'd at, or allow'd of the breach of plain moral commandments, ſince the man in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that doth not prohibit the ſin, that he may hinder, ſeems to injoyn it. I alſo obſerve,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50742:13"/>1. That according to your Opinion, whatever the <hi>Pope,</hi> and <hi>Cardinals,</hi> or other Biſhops do either al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, or condemn, is not binding as to the <hi>Faith,</hi> ſince the infallibility is lodg'd no where, but in a <hi>general Council.</hi> 2. If we look into the <hi>Cenſure,</hi> there is nothing relating to the breach of Oaths given to Princes, which is the higheſt truſt in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral matters, and withal, that the propoſitions are not condemn'd as contrary to the Laws of God, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as aſſertions, that promote impiety, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice; but <hi>ut minimum tanquam ſcandaloſas, &amp; praxi pernicioſas,</hi> [which is the manner of expreſſion that <hi>Alexander</hi> 7. makes uſe of in his <hi>cenſure, An.</hi> 1665.] <hi>as at leaſt ſcandalous, and pernicious to practice,</hi> and therefore to be condemn'd, which whether this doth not look like a <hi>trick,</hi> and <hi>juggle</hi> (becauſe you have encouraged me to uſe the word) you your ſelf ſhall be the judge; for notwithſtanding this <hi>cenſure,</hi> whenever the ſcandal ceaſes (which no one knows, how ſoon that may be) and they are judg'd no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger pernicious, the propoſitions may be again owned, and maintained. 3. It is moreover obſervable, that whereas former <hi>Popes</hi> have allowed theſe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, and Practices without condemning them, who knows, but the Succeſſors of the preſent <hi>Pope</hi> may, when they pleaſe, licence anew the propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are now condemn'd? 4. That ſome ſuch thing hath been formerly done, your <note n="*" place="margin">Ch. 26. m. p. 90.</note> Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary hath given you an inſtance, which you did not think fit to meddle with, nor to reflect upon, out of <hi>Archbiſhop Abbot's
<note n="†" place="margin">P. 11.</note> Preface to his ſix Lectures,</hi> where you will find,
<q>that <hi>Pius</hi> 5. the ſame <hi>Pope,</hi> who authoriz'd the <hi>Trent-Catechiſm,</hi> gave his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to ſome of the <hi>Engliſh Miſſionaries,</hi> that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50742:13"/>whenever any of them were called before a judge in <hi>England, he might either refuſe the Oath, or Swear, and anſwer ſophiſtically; poteſt Catholicus tractus coram hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticis vel recuſare juramentum (quod eſt prudentius) vel ſophiſticè jurare, &amp; ſophiſticè reſpondere ſuis inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogationibus.</hi>
               </q> And if you look into the Book called <hi>Foxes,</hi> and <hi>Firebrands,</hi> you will ſee there, that <hi>Heath</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> had a <hi>Bull</hi> with him dated <hi>An.</hi> 1. of the ſame <hi>Pius</hi> 5. allowing him to preach what Doctrine the <hi>Society of the Jeſuits</hi> ſhould order him for the dividing of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the diſpenſation given by <hi>Eugenius</hi> 4. and his <hi>Legate Card. Julian</hi> to <hi>Ladiſlaus King</hi> of <hi>Hungary</hi> to break his League with the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> for which he was ſo ſeverely puniſht in the unfortunate Battel of <hi>Varna,</hi> and ſome other ſuch examples, the Examination of Mr. <hi>Garnet</hi> is a very plain proof of this our aſſertion; for though ſome men call theſe little arts <hi>equivocation,</hi> and <hi>mental reſervation,</hi> as if they were ſmall, or no ſins, yet you fairly, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly condemn both alike, and I know few wiſe, and good men, but look upon both as alike ſinful, and perhaps the <hi>equivocation</hi> the more ſo, becauſe the deſign is more cunningly laid to deceive.</p>
            <p>And now I am talking of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> I think fit to mind you, that whereas you ſeem to ſay, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pap. miſrepre. p.</hi> 69, 70.</note> that it is a ſcandal upon your Church to affirm, that 'tis more lawful to be drunk on a Faſting day, than to eat fleſh, I have met with a <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſcobar. tr.</hi> 1. <hi>ex.</hi> 13. <hi>n.</hi> 74, 75.</note> of your commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, who will not allow a man to eat Fleſh on a Faſting day, but as to drink gives great indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, when he ſays, <hi>that a man may drink Wine even in great quantity,</hi> and if he happen to be drunk, <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderatio
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50742:14"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50742:14"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:50742:15"/>poteſt temperantiam violare, ſed non jejun ium He may tranſgreſs the Laws of Temperance, but he does not tranſgreſs the Laws of Faſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this I will not decide the controverſy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween your Adverſary, and your ſelf, whether the ſtory of S. <hi>Perpetua</hi>'s Viſion be ſeriouſly related, or droll'd on (who pay a great veneration to all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent writings, and can hardly think, that a Martyr in view of an Eternal Crown of happineſs would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge to any thing, that is light, or deſerves to be expoſed) but I have ſome things to ſay relating to that Viſion. As, 1. That it is very probably belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by moſt learned men, that <hi>SS. Perpetua,</hi> and <hi>Faelicitas</hi> were <hi>Montaniſts,</hi> among whom there were many <hi>viſions,</hi> which the reſt of the World gave no credit to; but this I ſhall not diſpute. But, 2. I averr, that it is very diſputable both from the <hi>viſion</hi> it ſelf, and from the quotations in St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Dinocrates</hi> were baptiz'd, or no. I know, your <note n="†" place="margin">Chap. 23. p. 84.</note> Adverſary ſays, he was baptized, and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> would fain have it ſo, but there is no convincing proof, that he was ſo; and the ſilence of the Writer of <hi>that Paſſion</hi> ſeems to imply, that he was not ſo. Now then I urge you with this <hi>Dilemma,</hi> either <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocrates</hi> was baptiz'd, or not; if he were not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd, (as it is very probable, becauſe his Father was a very violent Heathen, and ſo in all likelihood would not ſuffer his Son, being ſo young, to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd) then you have nothing to do with him in <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory;</hi> for, tho you have allotted an appartment there for the unbaptiz'd Children of Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, yet you allow no place there to the unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd Children of <hi>Heathen</hi> Parents, who with their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50742:15"/>
               <hi>Pagan</hi> Progenitors are condemn'd to Hell; unleſs we muſt reckon this ſtory with thoſe other of St. <hi>Thecla</hi>'s bringing the Soul of <hi>Falconilla</hi> out of Hell, or St. <hi>Gregory</hi>'s praying thence the Emperour <hi>Trajan,</hi> which later ſtory the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Munster. praef. ad Evang.</hi> S. <hi>Matth. Heb. p.</hi> 103/4</note> 
               <hi>Jews,</hi> who themſelves allow of a ſort of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> make ſport of; but if he he were baptiz'd, (as I profeſs, I cannot believe, tho St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays ſo) then it ſeems very hard, that a Child of ſeven years old, (when few Children are capable of underſtanding enough to chuſe to be wicked) ſhould be ſent to <hi>Purgatory</hi> for ſins, which he knew not of; for if that be true, which St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> ſays, that his Father probably carryed him to the Heathen Temples, as we will ſuppoſe it to be, this was the Father's ſin, and not the Child's, and ſo I cannot ſee, why <hi>Dinocrates</hi> ſhould be puniſht.</p>
            <p>And to confirm my conjecture, that he was not baptiz'd, I am apt to think, that in the Viſion the Water, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Paſſ. ſ. Perp p.</hi> 15. <hi>Ed. Oxon.</hi>
               </note> which <hi>Perpetua</hi> ſaw her Brother endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to drink of, but could not come at, was an Emblem of the Waters of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which he ſeem'd to endeavour after, and at laſt <hi>Perpetua</hi> her ſelf ſays <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Io. p.</hi> 5.</note>, that ſhe her ſelf was a <hi>Catechumen,</hi> when ſhe was apprehended, and that at that time ſhe had two Brethren both <hi>Catechumens;</hi> now if we reckon <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocrates</hi> for one of thoſe two Brethren of hers, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him to be dead ſome time before, (as I rather conjecture) I am ſtrongly inclined to believe, that while the Father was an obſtinate <hi>Pagan,</hi> the Siſter, and the other Brothers only <hi>Catechumens,</hi> that this younger Son, who was but ſeven years old when he died, was not baptiz'd, before he went out of the World; now if he were not baptiz'd, the Fathers
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50742:16"/>tell you, there was no hopes of Salvation for him; for to omit St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and the <hi>African Fathers,</hi> I will only inſtance in two remarkable paſſages, the one for the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Church out of <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Dog. Eccl. c.</hi> 74.</note> 
               <hi>Gennadius, Nullum Catechumenum, &amp;c. That no Catechumen, tho he die in a ſtate of good works</hi> (which is more than St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays of <hi>Dinocrates,</hi> for he accuſes him of Idolatry) <hi>can attain to Eternal life, unleſs he be a Martyr.</hi> And for the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church out of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>To.</hi> 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in Ep. ad Phi. p.</hi> 20.</note>, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Mourn over thoſe, who leave the world without Baptiſm; they deſerve your ſighs, and lamentations; they are out of the Kingdom of God among the unrighteous, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if all your former Arguments will not make us Converts, you tell us,
<note n="*" place="margin">Refl. p. ult.</note> that <hi>if a man aſſent to theſe Articles, as you have ſtated them, he ſhall have admittance into your Church,</hi> and probably ſo, for we know, you deal very gently with your new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, till you have ſecured them; but who knows how much further he muſt go, when he is under new Oaths of Obedience to that Church, who makes her <hi>unwritten Traditions</hi> (which no man knows, till ſhe reveals them) to be as much the <hi>Rule of Faith and Manners,</hi> as the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly binds all her followers to an <hi>Implicit Faith</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, whatever ſhe ſhall reveal? And I remember, that Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Annal. an.</hi> 1560.</note> records a report, that once there were more eaſie terms of Reconciliation propoſed by the <hi>Pope's Nuncio,</hi> viz. the allowance of the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in both kinds,</hi> and the confirmation of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Lyturgy,</hi> and probably many other things, ſo the <hi>Papal Supremacy</hi> were acknowledged; but we are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50742:16"/>very well ſatisfied,
<q> that St. <hi>Peter</hi> had no more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, than the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and that every Biſhop by Divine Right, is a Succeſſor of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and conſequently hath equal power in the Church of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> that the making more Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than we are ſure <hi>Chriſt</hi> inſtituted, is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment upon his Right, (and that the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your five additional Sacraments, is ſuch an encroachment) that the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Canon of the Old Teſtament (the <hi>Jews,</hi> till our bleſſed Saviour's time, being the only True Church of God) with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controverted Books of the New, are the only di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely inſpired Oracles, and a ſufficient <hi>Rule of Faith, and Manners,</hi> without the help of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha,</hi> or of unwritten <hi>Traditions:</hi> that General <hi>Councils</hi> are not infallible, much leſs the <hi>Pope,</hi> either ſingly, or with the Colledge of <hi>Cardinals;</hi> that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Communion in one kind, is robbing the people of what our Saviour gave them a right to; and that Prayers in an unknown Tongue are a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to St. <hi>Paul;</hi>
               </q> with many other ſuch points, which it is now needleſs to mention, for which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Members of the <hi>Church of England</hi> think fit to continue, where they are, where they enjoy all the forementioned bleſſings, with many others, which muſt neceſſarily be forfeited, when they embrace the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion.</p>
            <p>Thus have I curforily taken notice of your <hi>Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> in whatever <hi>material points,</hi> you have thought fit to ſpeak to, except that very weighty, and <hi>moſt material point</hi> of the power of <hi>Depoſing Princes,</hi> the thorow conſideration of which, was the firſt cauſe of my preſent undertaking. Now you encounter your
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50742:17"/>Adverſaries <hi>Golath-Argument</hi> (as you ſeen in ſcorn to call it, as <hi>Card. Bellarmine in the Praeface to his Anſwer to Barclay</hi> ſays, that writing in defence of <hi>Princes, Barclay</hi> came out like <hi>Goliah,</hi> to defie all the Armies of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) with this diſtinction <note n="*" place="margin">Refl. p. 9.</note>, that <hi>in all Councils there are ſome Articles of Faith, which all Catholicks receive, and ſome Conſtitutions, and Decrees relating to Diſcipline, and Government, which are not abſolutely obligatory,</hi> (ſo that I perceive, that in ſome ſort, and upon ſome conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, thoſe other Conſtitutions, and Decrees rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Diſcipline, and Government, are obligatory, <hi>i. e.</hi> upon condition, tho not abſolutely) and withal, you tell us as freely, that if the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine had been as evidently declared in former Councils, as ever Purgatory, or Tranſubſtantiation were in that of</hi> Trent, <hi>yet with you it ſhould be no Article of Faith.</hi> Which way of arguing (tho it be very generous) ſeems to me to deſtroy your diſtinction of matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> for if the <hi>Lateran Council</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine</hi> as a matter of <hi>Faith,</hi> and requir'd the belief of it under the penalty of an <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema,</hi> as the <hi>Trent-Council</hi> did <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> then either you muſt have believ'd, as the <hi>Council</hi> required, or elſe in matters of Faith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd by a <hi>general Council</hi> a man may think himſelf not bound to believe them; and if ſo, I ſee no other reaſon, why any other man may not as well refuſe to believe <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> upon your own principles. But if we allow of your diſtinction in your own ſenſe, I ſuppoſe, you will hardly allow another man to make the like deductions, and think himſelf at Liberty to follow his own dictates; for, if ſo, then the <hi>half communion, Prieſts Marriages, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in Latin, the Popes Supremacy,</hi> and many other ſuch
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50742:17"/>points being matters of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> every man by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of reaſon may give himſelf a diſpenſation to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve contrary to the definitions of <hi>Councils,</hi> if you allow your ſelf a liberty to believe the Princes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be depoſed, though it were defin'd as matter of <hi>Faith</hi> in a <hi>general Council.</hi> And it is remarkable, that for the better underſtanding of this diſtinction you recommend <note n="*" place="margin">Refl. p. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> to us, who, I am ſure, makes the <hi>Popes perſonal infallibility, his ſuperiority to a general Council, and his power of depoſing Princes mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to allow of your diſtinction between <hi>matters of Doctrine, and matters of Diſcipline,</hi> and that in <hi>matters of Faith</hi> from the definitions of a <hi>general Council,</hi> no man ought to vary, but in <hi>matters of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,</hi> though defined by the ſame <hi>Cooncil,</hi> a man is left at liberty; pray, tell me ſeriouſly, is every man left at liberty, or ſome men only? If every man, then the aſſertors of the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine</hi> have as much right on their ſide, as you have, (for the <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſpirit</hi> is not to be your guide in your Church any more, than in ours, and the aſſertors of that <hi>depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing power</hi> have <hi>Councils</hi> on their ſide, and <hi>Popes,</hi> and many private Doctors) and if you tell me, that you are not to follow your own prudence, but the Doctors of the Church, where you live, in what a <hi>general Council</hi> hath not decided as <hi>matters of Faith,</hi> then you muſt change Opinions with the climate, you live in (as <hi>Pere Cotton</hi> ſaid of himſelf, that in <hi>France</hi> he believ'd a <hi>general Council</hi> to be above the <hi>Pope,</hi> but in <hi>Italy,</hi> that the <hi>Pope</hi> was above a <hi>general Council</hi>) for if you inquire in <hi>France,</hi> whence, I ſuppoſe, you have your principles, as well as your arguments, they will tell you now, that the <hi>Pope</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:50742:18"/>hath no ſuperiority over Kings, and that they have condemn'd <hi>Sanctarellus</hi> his book, and burnt <hi>Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>'s; but if you inquire in the Neighbouring Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, they will tell you the contrary; it is well known, what the belief of <hi>Italy</hi> is in this point; and for <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> at <hi>Toledo, Jan</hi> 10. 1683. condemn'd the late cenſure of the <hi>Sorbon;</hi> and in the <hi>Low-countries D'Enghien a Profeſſor of Louvaine</hi> hath written in defence of the <hi>Popes power over Princes</hi> againſt <hi>Natalis Alexander,</hi> and poſitively averrs, that the <hi>French</hi> Opinion is either <hi>Hereſie,</hi> or <hi>next to Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> and that more Authors in your Church aſſert, than deny the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine</hi> (the preſent <hi>Pope</hi> urging that, and ſeveral other <hi>Univerſities</hi> to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the <hi>Decrees</hi> of the <hi>French Aſſembly, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>V. d'Engbien. p.</hi> 549. <hi>&amp;c. &amp; Jucieu. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſme, &amp; Papiſme mis en parallel. to.</hi> 2. <hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>ch.</hi> 3.</note> An.</hi> 1682. Among whom it is obſervable, that the <hi>Univerſity</hi> of <hi>Doway</hi> prayed the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> their new Maſter, to whom they were lately made Subjects) that he would not force them to change their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, leſt they ſhould be accuſed of taking up a new Theology with a new Soveraign) and if you go into <hi>Hungary,</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> there alſo condemn'd the Doctrine of the <hi>French Biſhops</hi> as erroneous, and ſchiſmatical <hi>Oct.</hi> 24. 1682. and when the <hi>Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Gran, the Primate of lower Hungary</hi> wrote againſt the Propoſitions of the ſaid <hi>French Aſſembly,</hi> an order was given to the <hi>Sorbon</hi> to cenſure the <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi>'s Book, which they refuſed to do, but upon this condition, that they might be allowed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the propoſitions, as if extracted out of ſome other Author, which looks like a fine fetch of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry. And now, <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pap. miſrep. p.</hi> 50.</note> 
               <hi>Where is three times the number, who diſown this Doctrine of depoſing to them, that own it,</hi> as you ſay? Whereas, beſides what hath been above
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50742:18"/>mention'd, the <hi>Author of the firſt Treatiſe againſt the Oath of Allegiance,</hi> p. 13. ſays,
<q>that the <hi>Depoſing Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> hath been the common received Doctrine of all School-divines, Caſuiſts, and Canoniſts, from firſt to laſt (afore <hi>Calvin</hi>'s time) in the ſeveral Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> yea even in <hi>France</hi> it ſelf, and even there of thoſe <hi>French Divines,</hi> that were moſt eager for their Temporal Princes againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> as <hi>Occam, Almain, Joh. Pariſienſis, Gerſon,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And is it not an argument of the great care, which your Church hath taken of the Perſons and Intereſts of Princes (which are ſacred) that every Writer of your Church, whether Prieſt, or Lay-man, ſhall have liberty freely to publiſh his thoughts about the rights of Soveraigns, and whether their Subjects, or the <hi>Pope</hi> may depoſe them? As if the Doctrine of Obedience to Superiors were ſuch a ſlight indifferent thing, that a man may with ſafety to his Religion, and Conſcience believe, either that the <hi>Pope</hi> may, or may not abſolve Subjects from their Obedience. A wiſe man would think, that there were a greater neceſſity to define ſuch a point (upon which the ſafety of Kings, and their Kingdoms depends) than to define the preciſe manner of our bleſſed Saviour's preſence in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, which had it never been defin'd (while all Chriſtians acknowledge him to be there) might have been the occaſion of much peace and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to <hi>Chiſtendom.</hi> And if you plead, that ſome men among us have aſſerted the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine,</hi> to this your <note n="*" place="margin">Ch. 20. p. 75.</note> Adverſary hath given you a full anſwer. For until you can ſhow, that our <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> and inferior Clergy in <hi>Convocation</hi> have owned any ſuch Doctrine, or countenanc't ſuch men in aſſerting it, you ſay nothing to the purpoſe; for we damn the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50742:19"/>by whomſoever vented, and our ſuperiors are ready to cenſure the aſſertors of it, if they durſt appear openly. Nor is it enough to ſay, <hi>that this hath been done by the French Clergy,</hi> which is equivalent to an act of our <hi>Convocation;</hi> for the agreement will not hold, becauſe the diſpute is not between the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Church, but between the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Roman-Catholick</hi> Church in this point; now we averr, that the whole Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> damns, and diſowns <hi>the Doctrine of Depoſing;</hi> but you tell us, that only a part of your <hi>Catholick Church</hi> doth ſo too, whereas a far greater part own, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it; we aſſert, that it is Hereſie to own the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but you dare not give it that name, leſt you offend <hi>his Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, it is plain from experience, that ſo far are the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the great men of your Church from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine,</hi> that thoſe few men among you, that have been ſo juſt, and ſtout, as to aſſert the rights of Princes, have fallen under the Church <hi>Cenſures,</hi> of which I need quote no more inſtances, than <hi>Widdrington</hi> of old, and <hi>F. Barnes</hi> (if he be yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live) and <hi>F. Welſh</hi> at this preſent Excommunicate for affirming it to be the Duty of Subjects to Swear <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance</hi> to their Prince, and to defend him even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, and all his <hi>Cenſures;</hi> whereas we daily ſee the aſſertors of the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine</hi> not only live, and dye in your Communion without Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but to be the moſt thriving men, and the ſooneſt preferr'd to dignities. So very true is that ſaying of <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ostenſ. err. Suareſ. c.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 918. <hi>ad cali. to.</hi> 2. <hi>de rep. Eccl.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Marcus Aut. de Dominis Archbiſhop of</hi> Spalato, <hi>that the Pope, and his followers are not pleaſed with any thing ſo much, as with the rendring the power of Kings, vile, weak, and contemptible,</hi> to which I will add, and the expoſing all, who defend it.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:50742:19"/>
            <p>And to convince you, that you your ſelf have not that venerable Opinion of the Majeſty of Princes, and the Duty, which their Subjects owe them, as you ought, I cannot but obſerve, that you not only tell us, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pap. repreſ. p.</hi> 50.</note> 
               <hi>that it is a diſputed point among your Doctors</hi> (as if it were one of thoſe <hi>School-points,</hi> which you mention p. 72. <hi>which may be maintain'd this way, or that way, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny breach of Faith, or injury to Religion</hi>) but withal, that whereas upon every other head of Doctrine, or Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, that you repreſent, you are frequent in quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons out of holy Scripture to prove your aſſertions (how pertinently applyed, your Adverſary hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd) upon this head of the <hi>depoſing power</hi> (as alſo when you treat of it more largely than of any other thing in your <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. § 4. <hi>p.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Roman Catholick principles,</hi> if that Book be yours) you quote not one text againſt Rebellion, you confeſs, that Rebellion againſt a Prince is <hi>contrary to the Fundamental Laws of the Nation, injurious to So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign power, deſtructive to peace, and Government, and by conſequence in his Majeſties Subjects impious, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> (where I ſhall not take notice of your limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the propoſition to his Majeſties Subjects, which hath no relation at all to the queſtion, <hi>whether the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of an Heretical Prince,</hi> as you account him, may not take up Arms againſt him) but why do not you ſpeak out, and ſay it is <hi>directly impious and damnable?</hi> (if you will not ſay, it is <hi>Heretical</hi>) being againſt an expreſs Law of God, that binds you to obey (even a <hi>Nero,</hi> or a <hi>Diocleſian</hi>)
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>not only for wrath, but for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake;</hi> that tells you, that <note n="†" place="margin">1 Sam. 26.9.</note> 
               <hi>no man</hi> (upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever) <hi>can lift up his hand againſt the Lords anointed, and be guiltleſs.</hi> For by your way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if the <hi>Fundamental Laws</hi> of a Nation may be ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by ſuch a Rebellion (and you know, the pretence
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50742:20"/>of all Rebels is <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Property</hi>) and the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment duly ſetled, peace promoted,</hi> and the <hi>Soveraign power, i. e.</hi> the Monarchy <hi>not injured,</hi> though a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Monarch may be (and yet your <hi>Depoſing Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> ſay, that it is no injury to an Heretical Prince to depoſe him, but a juſt Execution of the Laws) then a Rebellion may be lawful. But upon the principles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> if all theſe things could be ſecured, yet no man can be a Rebel, but he muſt be damn'd, becauſe the Laws of God forbid Rebellion, taking up Arms againſt a Prince, or endeavouring to depoſe him; for as long as the word of God ſtands firm, and the above-cited texts, with many others, are not blotted out of our Bibles, we think it directly damnable (and not only <hi>by conſequence,</hi> as you do) to take Arms againſt our Soveraign, let his Religion be what it will.</p>
            <p>So that, upon the whole, I cannot but ask you, while you have endeavoured to prove <hi>Purgatory, Invocation of Saints, &amp;c.</hi> from both <hi>Scripture,</hi> and <hi>Fathers,</hi> how happens it, that in the defence of the <hi>Rights</hi> of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> you quote neither? eſpecially, when you cannot but remember, that the Aſſertors of the <hi>Pope's Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>his power over Princes,</hi> are frequent in their doughty arguments from <hi>holy Scripture,</hi> ſuch as, <hi>God made two great Lights; behold, here, are two Swords; Feed my ſheep; riſe,</hi> Peter, <hi>kill, and eat,</hi> &amp;c. and is there no place to be found in all the ſacred Oracles, that forbids Rebellion, and requires Obedience? does not that inſpired Book injoyn all Chriſtians <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 22.21.</note>, <hi>to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things, that are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s,</hi> and <note n="†" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>to ſubmit to every ordinance of Man for the Lord's ſake;</hi> and if you are a Prieſt, are you not requir'd to teach others ſo to do <note n="*" place="margin">Titus 3.1.</note>? to <hi>put them in mind to be ſubject to principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50742:20"/>and powers, to obey Magiſtrates, and to be ready to every good work?</hi> Is there alſo nothing in the <hi>Fathers,</hi> that looks this way? doth not <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſay, that <hi>a Prince is inferiour only to God?</hi> doth not <hi>Irenaeus</hi> aver, <hi>that by the ſame power that men are made, are Princes conſtituted?</hi> Doth not <hi>Origen</hi> tell <hi>Celſus,</hi> that <hi>among the Chriſtians he ſhould not find any act of ſedition, or tumult,</hi> (notwithſtanding all their preſſures, and perſecutions) and doth not St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſay to the Emperor, <hi>we intreat thee, O Prince, we do not fight?</hi> not to multiply quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
            <p>And, before I leave this head, I cannot but remark, that whereas the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cep.</hi> 4. § 11.</note> 
               <hi>Trent Catechiſm</hi> allows, that <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors,</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are called <hi>Fathers,</hi> and ſo are included in the Commandment, (<hi>Honour thy Father, &amp;c.</hi>) which is more, than you acknowledge; yet they quote no place of <hi>Scripture</hi> to make this good, but the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Naaman, (ſic Naaman à famulis pater vocaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur)</hi> where his Servants call him <hi>Father,</hi> which does not look like fair dealing, for the Example does not reach the Doctrine, unleſs the Fathers of that <hi>Council</hi> praevaricate, <hi>Naaman</hi> being a Subject to the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> whereas they might have found without much ſeeking, that
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 24.11.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> calls <hi>Saul, my Father,</hi> who was his King; and in truth, the title was ſo proper to Princes, that the Kings of the <hi>Philiſtim</hi> were always called <hi>Abimelech,</hi> i.e. <hi>my Father the King</hi> by a general name, whatever their proper name was. Now I am loath to judg, that thoſe Fathers made uſe of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a Subject called <hi>Father</hi> by his Servants, that the Example might limit the Doctrine to ſubjection to inferiour Magiſtrates, when, had they inſerted the Example of <hi>David,</hi> it would plainly have proved the Obedience of Subjects to Soveraign Princes.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:50742:21"/>
            <p>And whereas the Fathers of the ſame <hi>Council,</hi> who were concern'd in the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> uſe to quote ſuch places of the <hi>Antients,</hi> as they thought pertinent to the Subject treated of, they having <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> § 17.</note> quoted <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. to prove that men ought to be obedient to the Higher Powers, confirm the Doctrine only by the teſtimony of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> (who it is true, ſpeaks plain, and to the purpoſe) omitting St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, Theodoret, Theophylact,</hi> and others on the place, who have told the World, that by <hi>every Soul,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> are meant <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as well as Laymen, nay the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, as ſays St. <hi>Bernard;</hi> but this probably would have unriddled the Myſtery, and expoſed a Doctrine, which they were not willing to diſown; the <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm,</hi> like the <hi>Canons,</hi> leaving every man, in many ſuch things, a great latitude; ſo that in ſhort, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to anſwer this Queſtion; Either Rebellion is againſt a <hi>Moral Law,</hi> or not; if it be, then the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot diſpence with it, and then, how happens it, that ſo many things of leſſer moment were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided in the <hi>Trent Council,</hi> while this was forgotten, or paſt by? If it be not againſt a Moral Law, then by your own principles, the <hi>Pope</hi> may diſpence with it, and what then becomes of all Obedience, when another <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. or <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. ſhall fill the Chair? And tho the <hi>Council</hi> would not condemn the <hi>Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Doctrine,</hi> yet why had not the Authors of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex Expurgatorius</hi> cenſured ſuch dangerous Books? for if we may judg of the ſenſe of the <hi>Trent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> by its <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> (tho made after the <hi>Council</hi> broke up) why may we not judg of its ſenſe by the <hi>Index,</hi> which was ordered to be made at the ſame time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the ſame men, who compoſed the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm?</hi> In which <hi>Index</hi> more than a few paſſages
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50742:21"/>are expunged, that interfere with the Papal Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, but not one poor ſentence condemn'd, that is deſtructive to the Rights of Princes.</p>
            <p>Here alſo, pray, ſuffer me to mind you of a bold aſſertion of a private man, as you are, and which, I am ſure, as things are now, you cannot accompliſh <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Introd. p.</hi> 11.</note>, for you undertake, that <hi>all Roman Catholick Nations in the World ſhall ſubſcribe to the condemnation of all ſuch principles, and practices</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> in your own words, of ſuch principles as <hi>deſtroy the peace of Nations with Fires, and Maſſacres, and rob Soveraigns of their Crowns, and Subjects of their Liberties</hi>) for I am ſure, there was a time, when all <hi>Roman-Catholicks</hi> were not of that mind, when the <hi>League</hi> was rampant againſt <hi>Henry</hi> 3. and 4. of <hi>France,</hi> in which one of them actually fell, and by the principles of which the other alſo was murthered; (not to mention, what the <hi>Emperors Henry</hi> 4. and 5. and our King <hi>John</hi> ſuffered) and when the <hi>Pariſian,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Maſſacres</hi> were ſufficient proofs to the contrary. Nor is it poſſible, even now, to make good your promiſe, ſince I have told you already, what the belief of the <hi>Spaniſh, Netherland,</hi> and <hi>Hungarian</hi> Churches are in this point, beſides what the <hi>Italians</hi> hold.</p>
            <p>Now againſt all this Doctrine you have nothing to object, but that this Doctrine hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pap. miſrepr. p.</hi> 51.</note> in <hi>France</hi> by the <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> there, and by the <hi>Univerſities</hi> of <hi>Caen, Rhemes, Poictiers,</hi> &amp;c. all which <hi>Univerſities</hi> are within the one Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> ſo that (tho there be no need of conſidering the Argument, becauſe it is only the ſentiment of <hi>one National Church</hi> againſt the reſt of what you call <hi>Catholick Chriſtendom</hi>) if I make it appear, that the <hi>French</hi> Church hath not always been of this belief,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50742:22"/>and perhaps is not ſo now, then all, that you ſay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that <hi>Topick,</hi> will be far from proving your aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; while withal I profeſs, that if what I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſay doth not reach ſo far as a conviction, and be only a well-meant Eſſay, yet the cauſe, which I maintain ought not to be prejudiced by it, becauſe the main poſition about the rights of Princes hath been already proved by other arguments, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities. And to evince this, I ſhall purſue the method which the famous
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Calviniſme, &amp; Papiſme mis en parallele, part.</hi> 3. <hi>ch.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Monſieur Jurieu</hi> hath laid down, adding here, and there my own obſervations.</p>
            <p>If therefore this be, and always hath been the Doctrine of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, then you have ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your argument aright, but if it hath not been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways their belief, then the preſent <hi>Gallican</hi> Church may be as well miſtaken, as the former, and if ſo, where is its authority? beſides, if the <hi>French</hi> Church do condemn the Depoſing Doctrine, and all the reſt of the <hi>Catholick</hi> World do aſſert it, then the <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is not on the ſide of the <hi>French</hi> Church, though never defin'd as a matter of Faith by a <hi>general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</hi> Now to prove, that the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine</hi> hath been the Opinion of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce one remarkable inſtance, and that is, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of <hi>Childerick,</hi> and the introducing of <hi>Pepin (the firſt King of the ſecond race)</hi> into his Throne, and I ſhall briefly tell the ſtory out of the <hi>French Hiſtorian,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Girard. du Haillan de l'Estate, &amp;c. l.</hi> 1. <hi>m.p.</hi> 66, &amp;c.</note> that I have now by me, who relates,
<q>that <hi>Pepin</hi> after his Conqueſt of the <hi>Sarazins</hi> did ſo honour, and reverence the Clergy, and repair'd ſo many of their Temples, that had been ruined, that the moſt holy men of that time thought him a Saint, whereupon aiming at the Crown, and finding nothing ſtick in his way, but the Oath,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50742:22"/>which the <hi>French</hi> had given to their King, he ſent to the <hi>Pope</hi> (whom he had before obliged) for his diſpenſation (<hi>Pepin</hi> having already gained the greateſt part of the <hi>Nobility, Eccleſiaſtick's,</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> to his party) the <hi>Pope</hi> readily granted a diſpenſation, the <hi>Clergy,</hi> as well as the <hi>Nobility,</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> acquieſc't in what was done, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging <hi>Pepin</hi> for their rightful King, and thruſting <hi>Childerick</hi> into a <hi>Monaſtery;</hi>
               </q> and ſo do <hi>Paulus Aemilius,</hi> and others alſo relate the ſtory, and among them <hi>Cardinal Perron,</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch. Childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric.</hi> 3. <hi>An.</hi> 751.</note> 
               <hi>Monſieur Meze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray</hi> ſays, that this was very likely done in that <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſembly</hi> held in <hi>March, An.</hi> 751. The <hi>Biſhops</hi> being there in great numbers, and <hi>Boniface Arch-Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Mentz</hi> in the head of them, who declared to the reſt of the Aſſembly the validity of the <hi>Pope's</hi> anſwer; and he intimates the reaſon, why they complied ſo readily with <hi>Pepin,</hi> becauſe he gave them a great ſhare in the Government.</p>
            <p>It is true, what our <hi>King <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Declaratio pro jureregio. p.</hi> 19.</note> James</hi> obſerves, that the elder <hi>Hiſtorians, Ado Viennenſis, &amp;c.</hi> ſay, that the <hi>States</hi> had dethron'd <hi>Childerick,</hi> and only got the <hi>Popes</hi> conſent to it, and confirmation of it, and ſo does <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſupr.</note> 
               <hi>Mezeray,</hi> and <hi>Monſieur
<note n="†" place="margin">Prerogat. of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and her Biſhops. ch. 29.</note> Maimburge,</hi> who is zealous in the caſe againſt the <hi>Papal power</hi> of <hi>depoſing;</hi> but which way ſoever <hi>Childerick</hi> were depoſed, his depoſition is a confirmation of what I undertake to prove; for if the <hi>Pope</hi> did it, and the <hi>French Clergy</hi> conſented, or the <hi>three Eſtates</hi> in <hi>France</hi> did it (of which the <hi>Clergy</hi> are the firſt) and the <hi>Pope</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, it is all one, the matter of Fact being plain, that they both thought it lawful to depoſe their Prince (for a leſs crime than Hereſie) becauſe he was dull, and unfit for Government. And we alſo know,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50742:23"/>that when the Line of <hi>Pepin</hi> was laid aſide, and <hi>Hugh Capet</hi> (<hi>the firſt King</hi> of the <hi>third Race</hi>) came to the Crown, there was a right Heir of the <hi>Carolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinian,</hi> or <hi>ſecond Race</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> alive, <hi>viz. Charles Duke</hi> of <hi>Auſtratia,</hi> or <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who was alſo laid aſide by the conſent of the <hi>States,</hi> of which the <hi>Clergy</hi> were the chiefeſt; it being
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>b. ſupr. an.</hi> 752.</note> 
               <hi>Monſieur Mezeray</hi>'s ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, that <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the laſt Male of the Line of <hi>Pepin,</hi> was deprived of the Crown, as <hi>Childerick</hi> had been; and the ſame
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Id. an.</hi> 987.</note> judicious <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> elſewhere gives an account, how it was done, that <hi>Charles</hi> being a Vaſſal to another King, and a ſtranger to his own Country, <hi>Hugh Capet</hi> being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry powerful, and eſteemed, was Proclaimed King at <hi>Noyon</hi> in an Aſſembly of the Lords, and in a little while after Anointed, and Crowned by the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Rheims,</hi> not one of thoſe, who were preſent at either Solemnity, claiming for <hi>Charles,</hi> but all giving their Oaths as well in writing, as by word of mouth to his Enemy; and when <hi>Archbiſhop Arnold,</hi> Brother to <hi>Charles</hi> was taken with him, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>France</hi> Aſſembled in <hi>Council</hi> at <hi>Rheims,</hi> degraded him of his Prelature for breaking his Oath to <hi>King Hugh,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as all his crime was the aſſiſting <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who was his lawful Prince.</p>
            <p>But to come nearer home. In the time of the <hi>League</hi> it is very plain, that the <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for the <hi>Leaguers,</hi> and allowed of the depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the two <hi>Kings, Henry</hi> 3. and 4. And whereas you may object, that ſome <hi>Popiſh Biſhops,</hi> and many of the <hi>Popiſh Nobility</hi> continued with <hi>Henry</hi> 3. to his death, and after that execrable parricide, with his Succeſſor <hi>Henry</hi> 4. yet <hi>D'Avila,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1589.</note> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1589.</note> 
               <hi>Rhodez,</hi> and
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1589.</note> 
               <hi>Mezeray,</hi> to name no other <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> ſay, that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50742:23"/>
               <q>after that barbarous aſſaſſinate, the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> who were the greater part of the Army, met, and, though ſome few were for adhering to the King without any conditions, yet the greateſt part thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bound to <hi>obſerve Divine, before humane Laws,</hi> (as they phras'd it) and at laſt both parties united in one upon theſe terms, that they would declare the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Navarre King</hi> of <hi>France</hi> upon conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he would change his Religion, ſince it would be ſtrange to their conſciences, and to the whole Chriſtian World, that one ſhould be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who was no <hi>Catholick;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon (many Prelates in the Camp declining even this moderate courſe) the agreement was made by a writing mutually ſigned, wherein the <hi>King</hi> ſwears, and promiſes upon the word of a King, to cauſe himſelf to be inſtructed in the <hi>Catholick Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> within ſix Months <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to maintain the <hi>Catholick Religion, &amp;c.</hi> and yet at laſt this did not pleaſe all, but many went over to the <hi>Leaguers.</hi>
               </q> Now here you ſee all the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>France</hi> (for they were all either of the party of the <hi>League,</hi> and it is not doubted, what their Opinion was, or of the <hi>Court</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,) were of Opinion, that the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France</hi> ſhould not be acknowledg'd, their rightful Soveraign, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he declared for the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Religion, nor would his own party admit him, till he had ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, and ſworn, as the <hi>Leaguers</hi> would not admit him, when he had ſo done; and this is worth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, that his own party, thinking he would dally with them, ſet him a certain number of days, wherein to give them his reſolution; and in all their conferences with the <hi>Leaguers,</hi> the <hi>Popiſh Lords,</hi> who were Friends to <hi>Henry</hi> 4 made this their Apology. And
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50742:24"/>upon theſe terms, ſays <hi>D'Avila,</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Mayenne</hi> himſelf promiſt by <hi>Villeroy</hi> his Agent to acknowledge him the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> though at the ſame time the <hi>Pope's Legate,</hi> and the <hi>Sorbon</hi> had made a <hi>Decree,</hi> that no agreement ſhould be made with the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and particularly with <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bourbon</hi> by which paſſage you may ſee, what was the Opinion of the Society of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> at that juncture, as by what elſe was done you may know the Opinion of the Prelates.</p>
            <p>And further the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rhodez</hi> confeſſes,
<q>That if the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Mayenne</hi> the head of the <hi>Leaguers</hi> had upon the importunity of the <hi>Pope, &amp;c.</hi> declared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> upon that nomination there was much appearance, and likelyhood, that all the <hi>Catholick Potentates</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> would have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd that King, whom the <hi>States</hi> ſhould have Elected, that the <hi>Clergy</hi> would have done the like, and the <hi>Nobility,</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> who followed not <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 4. But becauſe he had the Title of <hi>King,</hi> and would have made no conſcience to have quitted him for another, to whom the <hi>States</hi> had granted it.</q> And at laſt he ſubjoins,
<q>That it was high time for <hi>Hemry</hi> 4. to enter into the boſom of the Church, or to reſolve on a War, of which poſſibly he might never ſee the end.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things ſucceeded the death of <hi>Henry</hi> 3. But there were many remarkable accidents, that preceded it, which give you an account of the Opinion of the <hi>French Church</hi> of that Age. We know, the <hi>Sorbon</hi> is, and hath always been accounted the defender of the <hi>Gallican Liberties,</hi> and yet in the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>V. D'Avil</hi> &amp;c.</note> time of the <hi>League</hi> the whole <hi>Colledge</hi> (except <hi>Johannes Faber</hi> the <hi>Dean,</hi> and two Senior Doctors) unanimouſly determin'd, that <hi>Henry</hi> 3. by reaſon of the Murther of the <hi>Duke,</hi> and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50742:24"/>
               <hi>Cardinal</hi> of <hi>Guiſe</hi> had forfeited his right to the Crown, and that his Subjects were free from their <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance;</hi> nor were <hi>Faber,</hi> and the other two Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters (ſays <hi>Jurieu</hi>) diſſatisfied as to the point of Law. <hi>i. e.</hi> Whether the <hi>King</hi> were <hi>depoſable,</hi> or not, but as to the matter of fact, whether the crimes charged on him were true, or not, or if true, whether they deſerv'd ſo heavy a cenſure; and when the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France</hi> urged the <hi>Pope, Sixtus</hi> 5. to condemn the determination of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> with this argument, that ſuch a buſineſs did belong to <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Vicar,</hi> and not to a petulant <hi>Colledge</hi> conſiſting of a few paſſionate corrupted perſons; yet the <hi>Pope</hi> liked the cenſure too well to condemn it. Beſides, two or three diſſenters in ſo great a body, ſignifie nothing; for, had it been in an <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> or in a <hi>General Council,</hi> the majority would eaſily have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weighed ſo ſmall a number of contrary Votes; (and if the <hi>Syndick Faber</hi>'s aſſerting the Right of Princes, makes this no Decree of the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> then the <hi>Syndick Richer</hi>'s aſſertion, <hi>An.</hi> 1611. in his Book <hi>de Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica, &amp; politicâ poteſtate</hi> is enough to prove, that the <hi>Sorbon</hi> does not acknowledge the Government of the Church to be Monarchical) nor were the <hi>Sorboniſts</hi> wanting to countenance this their aſſertion, order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Boucher,</hi> and others to preach up the Authority of the <hi>Pope</hi> in ſuch caſes, and the Juſtice of the King's Depoſition; and there was a Book written in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>Cenſure</hi> (the Author of it believed to be our learned <hi>Stapleton,</hi> by others more likely, to to be the above named <hi>Boucher</hi>) <hi>de juſta abdicatione Henrici</hi> 3. and to make it appear, that the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of the <hi>League</hi> lookt on it as a quarrel on the behalf of Religion; it is remarkable, that the <hi>Duke</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:50742:25"/>of <hi>Parma</hi> left his own, and the publick concerns in <hi>Flanders</hi> in a very ill poſture; only that he might re-enforce the <hi>League,</hi> and relieve <hi>Paris,</hi> which was likely to have fallen into the hands of <hi>Henry</hi> 4. who beſieged it.</p>
            <p>And now we are come to the Times, that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Parricide of <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> (who, tho never ſo heartily reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was never forgiven the ſin of his firſt Apoſtaſie, as they called it, till his death) in the minority of whoſe Son <hi>Lewis</hi> 13. When the <hi>third Eſtate</hi> would have paſt a Law, that the <hi>King</hi> was depoſable for no cauſe whatever, the <hi>Clergy</hi> violently oppoſed it, and ordered the <hi>Cardinal de Perron</hi> to make a Speech againſt it, which after they had examin'd, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of in the <hi>Chamber Eccleſiaſtick,</hi> they attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to the convention of the <hi>three Eſtates,</hi> where he pronounc't it <hi>An.</hi> 1615. (which Speech our <hi>King James</hi> learnedly anſwer'd in his <hi>declaratio pro jure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio,</hi> where you may ſee it proved, that the Cardinal took upon him to aſſert, that the <hi>Pope</hi> or the Church had power to depoſe Princes, and that it was uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally owned in <hi>France</hi> ever ſince their <hi>Schools</hi> had been opened; and the event made it appear, what the deſign of the Speech was, after which the <hi>third Eſtate</hi> ſaw it impoſſible to go on with their deſign ſucceſsfully, and ſo declin'd it) and whatever <hi>F. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>b. ſupr. c. ult.</note> Maimburge</hi> ſays to the contrary, yet his own ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument confirms what I aſſert,
<q>That when this difference happened between the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and the <hi>third Eſtate</hi> (the <hi>two Chambers,</hi> as he calls them) the <hi>Clergy</hi> inform'd <hi>Pope Paul</hi> the 5. in their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to his <hi>Breve</hi> of <hi>Jan.</hi> 31. 1615. <hi>Angebamur non mediocriter, &amp;c.</hi> That they were troubled above
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50742:25"/>meaſure to ſee <hi>Catholicks</hi> tranſported with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet Zeal meddle with matters of Faith (where you may obſerve that the <hi>depoſing power</hi> is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by them to be a <hi>matter of Faith, earum rerum, quae ad fidem pertinent,</hi> though you deny it to be ſo) which did not belong to the <hi>third Eſtate,</hi> who were Lay-men, and Lawyers, but withal, they confeſs, that the determination of this point did belong to the Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> to themſelves, and the <hi>Pope, omnem hanc authoritatem penes Eccleſiam, eoſque ſolos eſſe, quos illa fidelium gregi praeeſſe voluerit.</hi>
               </q> By which it is plain, that that Speech was not <hi>one Doctors Opinion</hi> only, as <hi>Monſieur Maimbourge</hi> affirms, but the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole <hi>Chamber Eccleſiaſtick,</hi> or their whole Clergy. And, that the <hi>French Church</hi> afterward own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Opinion of that Speech, ſeems plain, becauſe the <hi>general Aſſembly</hi> of the Clergy <hi>An.</hi> 1665. gave the <hi>Abbot Gentil</hi> 6000. <hi>Livres</hi> to collect the <hi>Memoirs</hi> of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, which were afterward ſolemnly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewed by ſeveral <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Abbots,</hi> and then pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht, among which this Speech of <hi>Cardinal de Perron</hi> is printed, and approved, the whole ſcope of which, <hi>Maimbourge</hi> himſelf confeſſes, is inconſiſtent with the independent right of Princes, and their exemption from any <hi>depoſing power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, this Speech, that ſo few years ſince, was Printed among the <hi>Memoirs</hi> with ſo much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, and approbation, is now ordered to be left out of them; which is ſo far from being an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to incline any man to acquieſce in the judgment of ſuch a Church, that it may juſtly affright him from confiding in ſuch volatile changeable men, who in ſuch weighty matters vary their Opinions
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50742:26"/>ſo often from one extreme to another. And the reaſon is plain, the <hi>French Biſhops</hi> following the dictates of that <hi>Court;</hi> ſo that ſince the quarrel about the <hi>Regale,</hi> they have ſought to ſtoop the <hi>Pope,</hi> and probably to make his Election depend on the preſent <hi>French King,</hi> as it did antiently on <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Great.</hi> And of this I could give ſome likely proofs, but that the digreſſion would be too long.</p>
            <p>But againſt all this it is objected, That under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>King Lewis</hi> 14. the <hi>Sorbon, An.</hi> 1663. condemn'd even the <hi>indirect Power of the Pope over Princes,</hi> and aſſerted, that the <hi>King of France</hi> hath no other Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour but God; to which we anſwer, that the ſame <hi>Colledge</hi> did in the days of the <hi>League</hi> maintain the contrary, as I have formerly proved; and at laſt the <hi>Sorbon</hi> is not the Repreſentative of the <hi>French Church;</hi> nor can it be imagined, ſays the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 14.</note> Author of the <hi>ſecond Treatiſe againſt the Oath of Allegiance,</hi>
               <q>That thoſe men, who took upon them to vary from the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Decrees, or Definitions of <hi>Rome,</hi> would ever go about to ſet up an independent, or infallible Chair in the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> and deliver their Opinion ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as an Article of Faith in it ſelf, or as a Rule of Faith to others.</q> But the Objection is ſtrengthened, That the <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> aſſembled at <hi>Paris, An.</hi> 1682. as Repreſentatives of the <hi>French Church,</hi> did decree the ſame; to which we <note n="†" place="margin">V. Jurieu ubi ſupr.</note> anſwer, that the Declaration was made but by <hi>thirty</hi> or <hi>forty Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates</hi> within the verge of the Court, whereas in a free <hi>National Council</hi> the contrary might have been determined. But put the caſe that this had been decreed in a full, and free <hi>National Synod,</hi> yet neither could this have eſtabliſht an indefeaſible right; for
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50742:26"/>I remember, that in the <hi>Convocation</hi> under <hi>Henry</hi> 8. the <hi>King's Supremacy</hi> was decreed and eſtabliſht by our Biſhops (even by <hi>Gardiner, Bonner,</hi> &amp;c. who in all other things were zealous <hi>Catholicks</hi>) and yet I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you will be loath to grant, that for that reaſon the <hi>King</hi> had a juſt Right to that <hi>Supremacy.</hi> And this alſo ſerves to anſwer your Objection from the Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the <hi>French <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> againſt the <hi>Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Doctrine,</hi> becauſe not onely the greateſt part of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> did allow of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's Divorce from his firſt Wife, which the <hi>Pope,</hi> and perhaps you, would not allow to be lawful; but withal, the two moſt famous <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> (which to us are equivalent to all thoſe in <hi>France</hi>) and the moſt famous <hi>Monaſteries</hi> of the Kingdom, when this Queſtion was propos'd to them, <hi>An aliquid Autoritatis in hoc regno Angliae Pont. Romano de jure competat, pluſquam alii cuicunque Epiſcopo extero? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope had any lawful power in this Kingdom, more than any other forreign Prelate?</hi> The Anſwer was generally return'd in the Negative.</p>
            <p>Beſides, who knows not, that the generality of men ſpeak as their hopes of Preferment lead them? and that there was a great truth in that Obſervation of <hi>Aeneas Sylvius,</hi> That many men wrote in vindication of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Authority, and few for the Authority of a <hi>Council,</hi> becauſe a <hi>Council</hi> gave no Dignities nor Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices; but the <hi>Pope</hi> did. And I ſhould be glad to ſee the preſent <hi>French</hi> Clergy deal with the preſent <hi>Pope</hi> (when he meddles out of his Sphere with the Crowns of Princes) as their Predeceſſors did with <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fourth, who under the pretext of being a Mediator between the <hi>Emperour Lewis</hi> the <hi>Debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naire,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:50742:27"/>and his Sons, promoted the Rebellion, and was ſuſpected to come with a deſigne to excommunicate the <hi>Emperour</hi> and his Biſhops; for they proteſted,
<note n="†" place="margin">Ant. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. vit. <hi>Ludovici Pii.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si excommunicaturus ad veniret, excommunicatus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biret:</hi> i. e. That <hi>if the Pope came to excommunicate them, they would excommunicate him for acting contrary to the Authority of the ancient Canons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And at laſt we have Advice given us, <note n="*" place="margin">Nouvel. de la rep. de Lettres, <hi>An.</hi> 1685. p. 716, &amp;c.</note> That <hi>June</hi> 26. <hi>An.</hi> 1683. at <hi>Clermont</hi> in <hi>Auvergne,</hi> the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> publickly maintain'd four <hi>Theſes,</hi> in oppoſition to the deciſion of the <hi>French</hi> Clergy, <hi>An.</hi> 1682. 1. That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they call their Theſes Explanations of the Doctrine of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, the firſt Article of the Decree did not diminiſh the ſpecial Authority of the Church over Kings and Princes Chriſtian. 2. That the ſecond Article was not intended to weaken the <hi>Monarchick Primacy</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi> over the Church. 3. That by the third Article, they intended not to take from the <hi>Pope</hi> the Soveraign Power of diſpenſing with <hi>Canons,</hi> &amp;c. 4. That by the fourth Article, they intended not to deprive the <hi>Pope</hi> of all Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in matters of <hi>Faith.</hi> Which <hi>Theſes,</hi> as far as I know, yet paſs uncenſured. And the <hi>Janſeniſt,</hi> who goes under the name of <hi>René Clerc Tonſuré à l'Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſque de Paris,</hi> in his <hi>Syſtem of the Theology of the Gallican Church extracted from their Memoires,</hi> proves, that the <hi>French Biſhops</hi> are not ſuch Friends to Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heads, as they would appear to be; and that they take the Power from the <hi>Pope</hi> onely to place it in themſelves: affirming, <hi>That the French King cannot be judged by a Council except the French Biſhops be there,</hi> (implying, that then he may be judged) as if the <hi>last reſort</hi> were to them; and <hi>that the Declarations of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50742:27"/>the Pope against their King, ought not to be obeyed, till the Kingdom conſent thereunto;</hi> ſo that if the Kingdom conſent, the Depoſition is lawful: with other ſuch Poſitions. And the ſame Author affirms, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome <hi>Engliſh Gentlemen,</hi> Decemb. 1. <hi>An.</hi> 1679. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing themſelves to ſome <hi>Doctors of the Sorbon,</hi> had inclined them to decide for the lawfulneſs of our <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> ſent to them, that it was the <hi>King's</hi> pleaſure they ſhould not decide it: which makes it plain, that the <hi>Allegiance</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Church is founded on the <hi>Catholick</hi> Religion, and that an <hi>Heretical Prince</hi> hath not the ſame Right with <hi>the moſt Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though ſince that time <note n="†" place="margin">V. Cauſ. Valeſian. append. 6.</note> the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> An. 1686. hath given its approbation of the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> with the word <hi>Heretical</hi> in it, yet this is onely an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt acknowledgement of the Rights of Princes, by one <hi>Colledge</hi> of learned men; while in the ſame year the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> at <hi>Gaunt,</hi> in their <hi>Provincial Congregation,</hi> expreſly condemn'd the taking of the ſaid Oath. And who knows, but the <hi>Sorboniſts</hi> of the next Age may do as their Predeceſſors of the laſt did in the time of the <hi>League,</hi> contradict all that hath lately been aſſerted. Nor does the Condemnation ſignifie any thing in your ſence, ſince even a <hi>General Council</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not define any thing to be <hi>heretical,</hi> unleſs it be <hi>de fide,</hi> and the belief required under the penalty of an <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema:</hi> and when all this is done, if the matter be of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> you profeſs, you may ſafely refuſe to obey the <hi>Council.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which Obſervation I will adde one <hi>Remark</hi> more: That though <hi>Monſieur
<note n="*" place="margin">Apologie pour là Clergie.</note> Arnald</hi> hath written in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50742:28"/>vindication of the <hi>French Church,</hi> that they never owned the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine,</hi> yet if he be the Author of the <hi>Jeſuits Morals,</hi> (for though <hi>Monſieur Paſchal</hi> his Nephew have the honour of the Book, yet all men be lieve that <hi>Arnald</hi> had a great hand in the contriving it) he hath not dealt ſo ingenuouſly in this caſe, as he might: for when he quotes ſo many Paſſages out of the <hi>Moraliſts of the Society,</hi> what liberty they give to <hi>violate Sacraments</hi> or <hi>Oaths,</hi> to <hi>Lye</hi> and <hi>Equivocate,</hi> and <hi>to break all Truſts, Vows,</hi> and <hi>Promiſes,</hi> he never ſo much as touches on the many palpable Propoſitions in their Books, which encourage and allow of the breach of <hi>Allegiance</hi> to Princes.</p>
            <p>I have little more to ſubjoyn, but this: That whereas you appeal to the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> for the Faith of your Church, I have obſerved in that <hi>Council</hi> ſome things (how cunningly ſoever the <hi>Decrees</hi> were contrived, and how warily ſoever they were penn'd) which ſeem not to accord ſo well with your <hi>Catholick Principles.</hi> For inſtance: 1. <note n="†" place="margin">Seſſ. 22. de Sacrif. miſſ. can. 6.</note> The <hi>Council</hi> ſays, <hi>Si quis dixerit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If any man ſhall ſay, that the Canon of the Maſs contains any Errours in it, let him be Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema.</hi> And in another place
<note n="*" place="margin">cap. 4.</note> the <hi>Maſs</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>free from all Errour.</hi> Now if it be ſo, I ſuppoſe ſome of your Doctrines muſt fall to the ground, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by your <hi>Maſs.</hi> As, 1. The Doctrine of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation:</hi> for after the Conſecration, the Prieſt calls the Sacrament <hi>Bread and Wine; Offerimus panem ſanctem vitae aeternae, &amp; calicem ſalutis perpetuae:</hi> And afterward deſires God to <hi>look down upon it, as he did on the Sacrifices of</hi> Abel, Abraham, <hi>and</hi> Melchizedeck: And prays, <hi>That thoſe things might be carried by the hands of the holy Angels of God into Heaven.</hi> For how
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50742:28"/>are theſe Expreſſions ſuited to Chriſt's <hi>Corporeal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence?</hi> 2. All the Prayers of the Maſs relate to a <hi>Communion,</hi> and ſo are a conſutation of <hi>private Maſs;</hi> and yet the Prieſt in a <hi>private Maſs,</hi> when no one but himſelf receives, ſays, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quotquot ex hâc altaris,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That as many of us as have received the most holy Body of thy Son,</hi> &amp;c. 3. To inſtance in no more, the <hi>Prayer for the Dead</hi> in this Canon doth not relate to <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory:</hi> for the Prieſt ſays, <hi>Memento, Domini,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, O Lord, thy Servants, and thy Handmaids</hi> (and then names the Perſons whom he is to pray for) <hi>who have gone before us with the mark of Faith, and ſleep in the ſleep of Peace.</hi> Which are plain demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that thoſe Prayers were made before thoſe new Doctrines and Practices were the Belief and Cuſtoms of your Church, or elſe there are Errours in the <hi>Maſs,</hi> which the <hi>Council</hi> under an <hi>Anathema</hi> forbids any man to affirm.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Council</hi> declares, <note n="†" place="margin">Seſſ. 23. cap 4.</note> 
               <hi>Epiſcopos in Apoſtolorum locum ſucceſſiſſe;</hi> That <hi>Biſhops are the Succeſſors of the Apoſtles:</hi> and if ſo, then there being an equality a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſo there is alſo among <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and where then is the <hi>Pope's</hi> Supereminent Power as Succeſſor to St. <hi>Peter?</hi> and how is he above his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Biſhops, if they all ſucceed the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> to uſe St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Phraſe, <hi>Pari conſordio &amp; poteſtatis, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noris; In an equal right to power and honour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Council</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Seſſ. 4.</note> commands the interpretation of Scripture <hi>according to the unanimous conſent of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:</hi> and if ſo, we are well aſſured, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies between us will be eaſily decided on the ſide of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> for to the <hi>Fathers</hi> we are ready to appeal.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:50742:29"/>
            <p>And now after all this, ſuffer me to aſſure you, that though I love your generous dealing in the affix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your <hi>Anathema's</hi> at the end of your <note n="†" place="margin">Popery Miſ-repreſ. <hi>p.</hi> 117, 118.</note> Book, (wherein you deal much more candidly than many of your Brethren) yet I cannot but mind you, that you have left your ſelf and others, by reaſon of the generality of your Expreſſions, liberty to explain your meaning; and therefore I have added ſome <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma's</hi> agreeable to your own notions of things, (if I underſtand you aright) to which I ſhould be glad to find that you ſincerely ſay <hi>Amen:</hi> and it is as lawful for me, who am but a private perſon in the <hi>Engliſh Church,</hi> as it is for you to do ſo in the name of the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> And withal, I do engage to make good, that all theſe Opinions which I propoſe to be condemn'd, are maintain'd by ſome Writers of the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>He who pays true and proper Religious Worſhip to Images, let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Whoſoever confides in the Interceſſion of Saints and Angels, as much as in that of Jeſus Christ, for Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Whoſoever believes the bleſſed Virgin to have as much power in Heaven as her Son, and prays to her to command him, and begs from her, pardon of Sins, and the aſſurance of Salvation, let him be Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>He who does not believe that the Merits of Jeſus Christ are the onely meritorious cauſe of our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>He who believes that a Papal Indulgence doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Sins, or deliver from eternal Death, let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:50742:29"/>
               <item>6. <hi>He who believes that the performance of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Penances makes ſatisfaction for eternal Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due to his Sins, let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>He who ſpeaks irreverently of Holy Scripture, and calls it</hi> Aeſop<hi>'s Fables, a Noſe of Wax, and unſens'd Characters,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. <hi>He who believes that the Church hath power (in a General Council, or otherwiſe) to make additions to the Chriſtian Faith, let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. <hi>He who believes the Pope to have any perſonal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility, either</hi> è Cathedra, <hi>or in</hi> Conclave, <hi>let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10. <hi>He who aſſerts, that the Pope, or any other, hath any power to depoſe Princes, to diſpence with their Subjects Allegiance, and to authorize them to take up Arms against them, either upon the account of Hereſie, or for any other cauſe, let him be Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11. <hi>He who aſſerts, that the Pope, or any other, hath any power to diſpenſe with any Moral Law of God, and to give men a Licenſe to Murther, Forſwear, Lye, or Equivocate, let him be Anathema. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>12. <hi>He who believes any thing contrary to the Word of God, to Reaſon, and Antiquity, let him be Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13. <hi>He who ſays, that men are not bound to the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Ten Commandments, (and among them, of what we call the Second, you a part of the First) under pain of eternal Damnation, let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:50742:30"/>
               <item>14. <hi>He who thinks that Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks, and that Mental Reſervation may be uſed with men of another Perſwaſion, let him be A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>15. <hi>He who thinks that Attrition is enough to fit a man for Abſolution, let him be Anathema. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>16. <hi>He who thinks that any thing beſides a ſincere and true Repentance, can bring a man to Heaven, let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>17. <hi>He who believes that the modern Miracles of the Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are to be credited, as he cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits the Miracles of our Bleſſed Saviour and his Apoſtles recorded in Scripture, let him be Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>18. <hi>He who thinks Ignorance to be the Mother of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and wilfully hides the Holy Scriptures from the ſight and knowledge of the People, let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>19. <hi>He who ſays a man ought to obey his Superiours (whether Civil or Eccleſiaſtical) in things that are ſinful, let him be Anathema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>20. <hi>He who maintains any other Doctrines, than what were eſtabliſh'd by Christ and his Apoſtles, and believ'd in the Primitive Church, let him be Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema. Amen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe I give you as a <hi>Specimen;</hi> and when theſe are condemn'd, I ſhall think my ſelf much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable to be reconciled, than now I am.</p>
            <p>And becauſe you are a private Perſon, and whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you ſay, is but <hi>one Doctor's Opinion;</hi> and becauſe your Writers differ where your <hi>Infallibility</hi> is fixt, whether in a <hi>General Council,</hi> or the <hi>Pope,</hi> and if in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50742:30"/>the <hi>Pope,</hi> whether in his fingle Perſon, or in <hi>Conclave;</hi> you will oblige the World, if you uſe your intereſt to get theſe Doctrines Condemn'd by the <hi>Pope, ex Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra,</hi> (and ſo you will bind the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and others, who believe the <hi>Perſonal Infallibility</hi>) and by the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave of Cardinals,</hi> (for this will bind others of your Communion) and by a <hi>Council</hi> of all the Prelates of your Church, (and this will bind you, the <hi>French Church,</hi> and all others that call themſelves <hi>Roman Catholicks:</hi>) for unleſs this be done, we are ſtill where we were. And I ſhall tell you, that the regaining ſo conſiderable a part of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as the <hi>Church of England</hi> is, out of a ſtate of <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Hereſie,</hi> (as you are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in your great Charity to call it) is a Reaſon weighty enough to ſummon ſuch a <hi>Council,</hi> and to do what is required towards an Accommodation: and till this is done, all that you ſay elſe, is but the ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a little <hi>Holy Water,</hi> and <hi>gratis dictum.</hi> And this I write to you, becauſe you appear the Advocate of your Party, while I acknowledge that I make theſe Propoſals onely as a private Perſon; though I doubt not, but all the <hi>Prelates</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> would rejoyce to ſee ſo much done towards the heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Breaches of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>And here I thought to have put a period to this <hi>Eſſay,</hi> had not your <hi>Vindication</hi> of your <hi>Reflections</hi> come to my hands; upon which I cannot but beſtow a few <hi>Remarks,</hi> while your learned Adverſary will take care of a more full Reply. In which, among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, you undertake to <note n="†" place="margin">Proteſt, Popery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 16.</note> prove, by ſeveral inſtances, <hi>That our Church is guilty of miſ-repreſenting yours, becauſe it impeaches the Papiſts of Idolatry in the worſhipping of Images:</hi> and we acknowledge that ſhe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50742:31"/>does ſo impeach you; but withal we affirm, that there is a great difference between what is ſpoken by any man, or any Society of men, in a <hi>Homily</hi> or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and what is <hi>thetically</hi> laid down as an Article, or maintain'd in diſputation, (you your ſelves, as well as we, being often forc'd to make uſe of this diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſalve many Sayings of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> that they were ſpoken not <hi>Dogmatically,</hi> but <hi>Rhetorically;</hi>) but we need not depend on this Anſwer, for our <hi>Homily</hi> does not ſpeak of the <hi>Canons</hi> of your <hi>Councils,</hi> but of the received Opinions and Practices of your <hi>Church.</hi> Now that 'tis a current Opinion among many of your <hi>School-men, That the Image ought to have the ſame Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Prototype,</hi> I have already proved, out of Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine;</hi> and that the Practice of the Common People in this caſe, was very diſallowable, and much like the Idolatry of the Heathen, as I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>Trent-Council,</hi> is the Complaint in <note n="†" place="margin">Seſſ. 25. de Imag.</note> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of thoſe Fathers, and of ſome other of your Writers in particular: ſo that herein the <hi>Homily</hi> ſpeaks but the ſence of your own Authors, and with Juſtice, cenſures the Uſages of the People of your Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. And if what your <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Council</hi> ſays, be true, <hi>That the Idolatry of the Heathens did conſist in their putting their trust in their Idols,</hi> he who conſiders how much more Worſhip there is paid to the ſame Images of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> (at <hi>Loretto, Monferrat,</hi> &amp;c.) than to other her Images elſewhere, (which can as well put the People in mind of the <hi>Mother of God,</hi> as thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Shrines) will be perſwaded, that the generality of your Communion put their truſt alſo in the Image, as did the Heathens in their Idols.</p>
            <p>Now, to vindicate your Church from Idolatry in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50742:31"/>this caſe, though you <note n="†" place="margin">Proteſt. Pop. <hi>p.</hi> 33.</note> acknowledge, <hi>That you do give Religious Honour to Images,</hi> yet you ſay, That <hi>that Honour cannot be called Idolatry, unleſs it makes a God of that to which it is paid.</hi> But does not the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Commandment</hi> (as we reckon them) forbid the worſhipping of the true God by an Image? And do not the worſt of Idolaters ſay, That they do not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Image, but the God, who is repreſented by it? Doth not <hi>Celſus</hi> ſay ſo much on the behalf of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Idolaters to <hi>Origen</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 7. p. 373. <hi>Orig.</hi> contr. <hi>Celſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Who, but a perfect Fool, thinks an Image made of Stone or Timber, of Braſs or Gold, to be a God?</hi> &amp;c. And for the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they fell into Idolatry in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by worſhipping the <hi>Golden Calf,</hi> they onely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt it as a repreſentation of the true God: for the Feaſt that was ſet apart for it, is called
<note n="†" place="margin">Exod. 32.5.</note> a <hi>Feast held to Jehovah,</hi> which is the incommunicable Name of the onely true God. (And the like might be ſaid of the <hi>Calves</hi> in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi>) But perhaps you are of the opinion of ſome men of Eminence in your own Communion, (and whoſe Books have never been, that I know of, condemn'd) who think that the Worſhip of the Golden Calf was not Idolatry: for ſo <hi>Moncoeus</hi> in his <hi>Aaron Purgatus</hi> exprefly affirms, as <note n="*" place="margin">c. 7. p. 49.</note> 
               <hi>Greg. de Valentia</hi> in his <hi>Apologetic</hi> for <hi>Idolatry,</hi> (a bold Title for a Book written by a Chriſtian Prieſt!) argues from 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3. that becauſe the Apoſtle doth forbid <hi>unlawful Idolatries,</hi> (<hi>abominable Idolatries,</hi> as our <hi>Tranſlation</hi> renders it) that therefore there is ſome <hi>Idolatry</hi> that is lawful, which is that of the <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you object, <note n="†" place="margin">Proteſt. Pop. <hi>p.</hi> 34.</note> that <hi>we our ſelves are by this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument guilty of Idolatry, by bowing to the Altar, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50742:32"/>to the Name of Jeſus, and by kneeling at the Sacrament,</hi> Whereas, I muſt tell you, that we bow not to the <hi>Altar,</hi> but towards it, toward the <hi>East,</hi> where the <hi>Chriſtian Altar</hi> always uſed to ſtand, (and toward which part of Heaven the Primitive Chriſtians uſed to direct even their private Devotions;) nor do we bow to the Name, but at the Recital of the Name of our bleſſed Saviour: ſo that we pay no Religious Worſhip to the <hi>Altar,</hi> or to the Syllables of that Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Name, (as you confeſs you do to <hi>Images</hi>) and when we kneel, we profeſs we do not worſhip the Sacramental Elements, nor the Body and Bloud of Chriſt hid under the Accidents of Bread and Wine; but we kneel, becauſe then we pray, and we worſhip God, to whom we direct our Prayers: ſo that theſe actions are not external acts of Adoration to any thing that is ſeen, or heard, but onely to God. But by this way of arguing. I perceive, <hi>the Cauſe</hi> wants aſſiſtance, when you borrow Arguments from our Diſſenters to aſſault our Church with: for theſe are their little Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections that have been ſo often hiſt off the Stage.</p>
            <p>You further tell us, That <hi>it is the intention of the Perſon who pays the Worſhip, that makes the Worſhip either idolatrous or lawful.</hi> And if ſo, pray tell me, if a Chriſtian in the <hi>East Indies</hi> ſhould go into a <hi>Pagod,</hi> and bow down before one of their <hi>Images,</hi> and pay it in all reſpects the ſame outward Adoration that its moſt bigotted Votaries offer it, and at the ſame time <hi>intend</hi> his Worſhip towards the <hi>bleſſed Trinity;</hi> does this man, by virtue of his <hi>intention,</hi> eſcape the guilt of <hi>Idolatry?</hi> And I put you this Queſtion the more willingly, becauſe ſome of your <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it in the affirmitive, and acquit the votary of <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:50742:32"/>and I would willingly know your Opinion: for if you conſult the
<note n="†" place="margin">Let. 5. p. 61. Edit. Lat. Colon. <hi>An.</hi> 1658.</note> 
               <hi>Provincial Letters,</hi> the Author of them will tell you, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in <hi>China,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places of the <hi>Indies,</hi> taught the People that they might publickly worſhip the Idols of the Country, <hi>Cacin choan,</hi> and <hi>Keumfucum,</hi> ſo they directed this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration of theirs intentionally to the Image of our bleſſed Saviour hid under their Cloaths; and that this is no Calumny, the ſame Author ſays <note n="*" place="margin">P. 62.</note>, That the Practice was complain'd of, and cenſured at <hi>Rome, July</hi> 9. <hi>An.</hi> 1646. But notwithſtanding that Cenſure, if your way of arguing be good, the Practice is ſtill lawful.</p>
            <p>Now to evade your Adverſaries Argument, <hi>That intention cannot alter the nature of actions, which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd by either Divine or Humane Law;</hi> you ſhift the force of the reaſoning, by making a Plea from the ſame Principle for the <hi>Quakers,</hi> (and probably it is well done of you, to turn Advocate for a <hi>Sect</hi> which owes its Original to the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and other <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> of your own Church) becauſe, if <hi>intention cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the nature of actions determined by Law,</hi> no Oaths can be lawful, nor the payment of civil Honour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of, becauſe the Scripture ſays, <hi>Swear not at all, and let your communication be yea, yea, nay, nay, and you ſhall not be called Maſter,</hi> &amp;c. And the Anſwer would ſignifie ſomething, if you could ſhew us any place of Scripture where ſuch <hi>Worſhip</hi> hath been paid to <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> notwithſtanding the divine determination to the contrary, as we can ſhew you for the allowance of thoſe things which you object: for we there read, that notwithſtanding the prohibition, the Apoſtles did allow of the Title <hi>Lord,</hi> or <hi>Sir,</hi> or <hi>Maſter;</hi> for St.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50742:33"/>
               <hi>Philip</hi> expreſt no diſlike, when <note n="†" place="margin">Johan. 12.21.</note> the <hi>Greeks</hi> gave him that appellation; nor St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 16.30.</note> when the Jaylor at <hi>Philippi</hi> treated them with the ſame Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. And by <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> &amp;c. the Holy Writ onely forbids vain and raſh Swearing, and Perjury, and double Dealing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for it in other places tolerates and requires <hi>Oaths, which,</hi> ſays the <hi>Apoſtle, are the end of all ſtrife.</hi> After which, you will do well to ſhew any place of Holy Scripture, that countenances the <hi>Worſhip of Images,</hi> and we ſhall willingly acknowledge the parity of Reaſon: for it is not the intention of the Perſon commanded, but of the Lawgiver, that makes an action lawful: for did a mans own intention legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate his actions that are otherwiſe forbidden by any Law divine or humane, then a man may <hi>do evil, that good may come there of,</hi> expreſly againſt St. <hi>Paul;</hi> a man may commit Murther, Sacriledge, and every other groſs ſin, as ſome men have done, and plead for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he intended nothing but Reformation, and the advancement of Religion; as the men in our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's</hi> time perſecuted the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to death, with an intention to <hi>do God ſervice:</hi> but the intention of the Lawgiver, when made known, is that which legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates the actions of the ſubject either in matters purely civil, or in matters of Religion, of which latter ſort is the <hi>Worſhip of Images;</hi> which I ſhall acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be lawful, when you ſhall have ſhewn that it is agreeable to the intention of our ſupreme Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver.</p>
            <p>But the further management of this Argument, I leave to your other Antagoniſt, while I obſerve, that <note n="†" place="margin">Proteſt. Pop. <hi>p.</hi> 25.</note> you ſhift him off with no other Anſwer, but this: <hi>That a Queſtion or two is</hi> (in his opinion) <hi>a confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50742:33"/>the Reflecter,</hi> becauſe you are ask'd, <hi>Whether all your Repreſentations are conformable to the ſenſe of the</hi> Trent-<hi>Council and Catechiſm?</hi> which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready proved they are not, particularly in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>aſſiſtance of Angels and Saints.</hi> which you ſay, conſiſts <hi>onely in their Prayers,</hi> while the <hi>Council</hi> and <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> beſides their <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> mention their <hi>Merits</hi> and <hi>Aid.</hi> And whereas, when he objects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Pope's licenſing the Biſhop of</hi> Condom<hi>'s Book,</hi> that <hi>Canus</hi> with judgment avers, <hi>That whatever the Pope determines privately, maliciouſly, and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, is not to be accounted the judgment of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick See;</hi> you rejoyn, that the <hi>Pope's private deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> of any Opinion, doth not hinder it from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the judgment of the Apoſtolick See,</hi> unleſs it be alſo determined <hi>maliciouſly</hi> and <hi>inconſiderately;</hi> I cannot underſtand <hi>Canus</hi> in that ſence, but that, whatever is determined either <hi>privately,</hi> or <hi>maliciouſly,</hi> or <hi>inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately,</hi> is not the judgment of the <hi>Apoſtolick See:</hi> for if this be not ſo, then a <hi>private determination,</hi> how <hi>malicious</hi> ſoever it can be, ſo it be upon due <hi>conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> may be the <hi>judgment of the Apoſtolick See.</hi> And who knows, but the preſent <hi>Pope</hi>'s allowance of the <hi>Biſhop of Condom</hi>'s Book, may be the product of malice, of his ſpleen againſt the <hi>French Hereticks,</hi> as he calls them, for whoſe Extirpation he hath ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly by his Letters thanked the <hi>French King?</hi> And if <hi>Malice</hi> may invalidate the <hi>Papal Judgment,</hi> why may not <hi>Favour, Affection,</hi> or <hi>Fear,</hi> when they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in ſuch Determinations, render them equally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valid? And if ſo, why may not the reaſon of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Pope's</hi> not cenſuring the <hi>French Clergie</hi> in the matters relating to the <hi>Papal Power over Princes,</hi> be his <hi>fear,</hi> leſt that Victorious Prince ſhould either ſet
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:50742:34"/>up a <hi>Patriarch</hi> of his own in <hi>France,</hi> or by an Army eſtabliſh his Right in <hi>Italy,</hi> and make the <hi>Pope</hi> depend on him for his Election.</p>
            <p>But to confirm the Authority of the <hi>Biſhop of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi>'s Book, you ſay, <hi>That it was printed at</hi> Rome, <hi>tranſlated into divers Languages, and atteſted by the Pope and divers Cardinals,</hi> &amp;c. Will you allow of all that hath been publiſh'd for <hi>Catholick Doctrine</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> with the ſame or the like approbation? Were not Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi>'s <hi>Annales</hi> (to inſtance onely in one Book) printed at <hi>Rome</hi> in the Preſs belonging to the <hi>Vatican</hi>-Palace? Did not Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> V. prefix a very large Epiſtle in commendation of the Author, and the Work? Was it not magnified by the <hi>Roman Cardinals?</hi> Was it not tranſlated into <hi>Italian, German, Poliſh,</hi> and other Languages, and the <hi>two first Tomes</hi> of it into <hi>Arabick?</hi> Now if ſuch a Recommendation be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make known the Sentiments of your Church, then how comes it to paſs, that thoſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Annals</hi> are not received in <hi>France</hi> in thoſe things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to Regal Power, nor in <hi>Spain</hi> in what relates to the Right to the Kingdom of <hi>Sicily?</hi> And if you do allow of the <hi>Annals,</hi> you muſt not onely interfere with the fore-named Churches of your Communion, but you muſt alſo acknowledge, what you will be loath to own, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath a right to diſpoſe of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Kingdoms, as in truth that Cardinal hath inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled him to almoſt all the other Kingdoms of the World by name.</p>
            <p>It is alſo obſervable, that the Biſhop of <note n="†" place="margin">P. 50. Edit. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſ.</note> 
               <hi>Condom,</hi> when he ſpeaks of the <hi>Pope,</hi> mentions the <hi>Primacy;</hi> but for the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine,</hi> he ſays, <hi>It is not neceſſary
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:50742:34"/>to ſpeak of it:</hi> adding in general, <hi>That all Catholicks acknowledge a Head eſtabliſh'd by God to conduct his whole Flock in his paths, which thoſe who love Concord among Brethren, and Eccleſiaſtical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimity, will most wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly acknowledge.</hi> By which expreſſion every man is left to his own Sentiments in that point; and it is no wonder, that the <hi>Pope</hi> (though he does believe his own <hi>Power of Depoſing Princes</hi>) doth approve of this Book, for the Phraſe of <hi>conducting the whole Flock of Christ,</hi> is as eaſily to be conſtrued, as <hi>paſce oves meas,</hi> to ſignifie the <hi>Depoſing of Princes</hi> whenever the <hi>Pope</hi> pleaſes. So that we ſee, that even this ſeeming Enemy of the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine,</hi> dares not openly condemn it, but leaves it as a probable Opinion, and <hi>what 'tis not neceſſary to ſpeak of;</hi> ſo that every <hi>Pope</hi> hath ſtill his liberty to declare any Prince a Heretick, and then to proceed to Excommunicate, and to Depoſe him; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, a <hi>Clement,</hi> a <hi>Ravilliac,</hi> or any other Aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine, may proceed to murther him, becauſe he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alſo is left at liberty to believe that the <hi>Pope</hi> is in the right, when he hath depoſed a Prince, and that he ought, as much as lies in him, to obey him in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch Criminals to condign puniſhment.</p>
            <p>At laſt <note n="†" place="margin">Proteſt. Pop. <hi>p.</hi> 29.</note> you tell us, <hi>That a man may be admitted into your Church, notwithſtanding his refuſal to admit the Depoſing Doctrine, and the Pope's Infallibility, but as they are ſtated by the Repreſenter,</hi> i. e. <hi>not as Articles of Faith.</hi> But this ſeems to imply, that no man of your Communion ſhall dare to condemn the Doctrines, which muſt ſtill be look'd on as probable and diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; ſo that the ſafety of Princes and Kingdoms, and the guidance of the Church in matters of Faith (which depend on the plain ſtating of the <hi>Pope's Power</hi> and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50742:35"/>
               <hi>Infallibility</hi>) muſt ſtill be left at the mercy of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onative men, who may take liberty to diſpute and write about theſe great and weighty points <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> as themſelves think fit.</p>
            <p>And whereas your Adverſary quotes <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and <hi>Canus, That General Councils cannot erre even in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Diſcipline and Government</hi> (decrera morum) <hi>when they relate to things neceſſary to Salvation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the whole Church,</hi> you
<note n="*" place="margin">Proteſt. Pop. <hi>p.</hi> 32.</note> deny, that the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine is of that nature.</hi> But are not the plain Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Morality neceſſary to Salvation, as well as Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith? If not, then nothing but Infidelity damns a man; and if a man's Faith be Orthodox, it is no matter for his Converſation: If they are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is not Obedience to Princes one of the moral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God? And if ſo, is not the practice of that Obedience neceſſary to Salvation? and is not Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience (which neceſſarily follows the <hi>Depoſing Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi>) a great ſin? And if ſo, deſtructive of the hopes of Salvation. And that <hi>it concerns the whole Church,</hi> is eaſily proved, becauſe Princes are its Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing-Fathers.; and what Evils have fallen upon your own Church by ſuch raſh Attempts, ſome of your own Authors will tell you, is plain from the inſtance of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. Beſides, the whole Chriſtian Church and its Welfare, is concern'd in the Doctrine: for though all the Princes of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> have never been depoſed at once, yet what is done in one Country, may be done throughout all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and ſo the whole Church actually concern'd in the ſad effects of the Doctrine: And had the <hi>Empire</hi> been as intire un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Henry</hi> IV, as it was under the elder <hi>Emperours,</hi> his Depoſition had actually concern'd the whole Church.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:50742:35"/>
            <p>And becauſe you call that aſſertion, that <hi>the Pope hath not condemn'd the no-depoſing Power, becauſe he wants power ſo to do,</hi> an <hi>Oracle,</hi> and ſay, <hi>you look for an Argument to prove it.</hi> It is plain from Hiſtory, that thoſe <hi>Popes</hi> who have been rich, and ſtout, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, have adventured on the practice of Depoſing (while others of lower Spirits, leſs Wealth and Haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs, have been afraid of the Attempt) we are not ignorant what the <hi>Dictates</hi> of <hi>Pope Gregory</hi> VII. are, and how buſie he was, being back'd by the <hi>Counteſs Maud,</hi> who ſupported him with her intereſt; nor what <hi>Innocent</hi> III, <hi>Sixtus</hi> V, and ſome others have done in imitation of him. Nor is it unknown to the World, what Pope <hi>Paul</hi> V. thundered againſt the <hi>Republick of Venice,</hi> What <hi>Pius</hi> V. did here in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> X. in <hi>Ireland</hi> during the Rebellion there: for what was it that encouraged thoſe hot <hi>Popes</hi> to go ſo far, but that they thought their intereſt, at leaſt in the Church-men, ſo great, that the Countries would immediately have ſhaken off their Soveraigns? And what is it that cauſes the preſent <hi>Pope</hi> to ſpare the <hi>French King</hi> about the <hi>Regale,</hi> but that he is afraid of him, and knows he wants power to compel him? Nor need the Argument ſeem ſo ridiculous to you, ſince Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (a man from whom moſt of your Writers borrow all their Materials) doth not onely affirm, that the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> under the <hi>Heathen Emperours,</hi> did not take up Arms againſt them, <hi>becauſe they wanted power,</hi> but avers againſt <hi>Barclay</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Tom. 3. Oper. c. 6, 7, 8. p. 874, &amp;c.</note>, that the <hi>ancient Popes did not exert their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority against the Emperours</hi> Conſtantius <hi>and</hi> Valens, &amp;c. <hi>not becauſe they had no right,</hi> ſed quod Reges, <hi>&amp;c. but becauſe without great damage the Church could
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:50742:36"/>not compel them;</hi> but that <hi>the Popes did exert their Authority against</hi> Leo Iſauricus, Henry IV. <hi>and</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deric <hi>becauſe they were able to compel them. That</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian <hi>was very powerful, and attended with many armed Legions, against which an unarm'd Multitude ſignified nothing; that it was a falſhood that all his Army were Chriſtians, and that St.</hi> Gregory <hi>affirms, that the Church made uſe of no other Remedy but her Tears,</hi> quia decrant vires, <hi>becauſe ſhe wanted ſtrength to reſist the Tyranny.</hi> So that, pray anſwer your own <hi>Cardinal,</hi> or elſe acknowledge, that your Adverſary ſpeaks ſuch <hi>Oracles</hi> as may be confirm'd from ſome other Topick, beſides the authority of the Aſſertor.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhall put a period to theſe <hi>Remarks,</hi> when I have minded you of two things which are your own Conceſſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That <note n="*" place="margin">Proteſt. Pop <hi>p.</hi> 6, 7, 17, 18.</note> upon the confideration of what is here charg'd, the ſalvation of every Roman Catholick's Soul depends, that their Eternity is at ſtake; and that if Popery be guilty of what your Anſwerer ſays it is, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into your thoughts, that there is any room for it</hi> (or its Followers) <hi>in Heaven: That all our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs died for a good Cauſe, and are doubtleſs in Heaven: That ſuch Tenents bid open defiance to true Honeſty and Chriſtianity, ſtrike at the World's Redeemer, and are impoſſible to be entertain'd by any, who is one degree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a Beast.</hi> Theſe are the Concluſions I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, of a wiſe, a modeſt, and a good man; but then it behoves you ſeriouſly to conſider whether this Charge be not true, and whether your Adverſary be not to be acquitted of wronging your Church, (of which the impartial Reader will be the moſt compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:50742:36"/>Judge) and withal to think, whether thoſe <hi>School-men,</hi> and other Writers of your Communion, that do own all the Doctrines charg'd upon you, be not by your own Verdict, <hi>Men of no Honeſty, no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and but one degree above Beaſts:</hi> For by this Conceſſion every unbyaſt perſon is able to ſatisfie himſelf which is the true Religion, that which allows its Followers to aſſert the Doctrine of <hi>Depoſing Princes,</hi> to pay <hi>Religious Worſhip to Images,</hi> to expect <hi>more than interceſſion from Saints, Angels,</hi> &amp;c. or that which is directed by the Revelations made in Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and by the unanimous Interpretations made of thoſe Scriptures by the ancient Fathers, as the <hi>Church of England</hi> expreſly doth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That you follow the methods of the <hi>French Church</hi> [which is ſo far from being the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> even in your ſence of the word, that it is but a ſmall part of it] from them you take your Principles, from the <hi>Biſhop of Condom,</hi> and <hi>Monſieur Veron;</hi> and after their Example, you make your complaints of being <hi>miſ-repreſented:</hi> for ſo the <hi>Gallican Biſhops</hi> did in their late <hi>general Aſſemblies,</hi> held <hi>July</hi> 11. <hi>An.</hi> 1685. complain of <hi>being miſ-repreſented, and of the Calumnies, Injuries, and Falſities, which the Reformed Churches lay to their charge;</hi> deſiring that King, in their <hi>Petition</hi> prefixt to the <hi>Acts</hi> of that <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> to revoke all the <hi>Edicts</hi> made in behalf of the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> becauſe <hi>permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted onely in times of diſturbance, and for reaſons which no longer ſubſist:</hi> which though they afterwards modifie and limit onely to the paſſing an <hi>Edict</hi> to forbid the calumniating their Religion, yet every conſidering man ſees what they aim at. And upon this Addreſs the King paſt an <hi>Edict, Aug.</hi> 23. forbidding all the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50742:37"/>
               <hi>Reformed</hi> to preach or write any thing againſt the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion,</hi> either directly or indirectly, and to allow them the liberty of the Preſs onely for printing the <hi>Confeſſion of their Faith, their Prayers, and the Rules of their Diſcipline,</hi> but no other Books written by the <hi>Reformed Divines</hi> of that Kingdom; and what the effects of that and other <hi>Edicts</hi> have been, every wiſe Obſerver hath ſeen.</p>
            <p>
               <q>May our bleſſed and holy Saviour, the true and undoubted Head of the Catholick Church, heal all the Breaches thereof, convert all Hereticks to the knowledge of the Truth; ſhame, and bring back all Schiſmaticks into the Unity of his Myſtical Body, that we may be one Sheepfold under one Shepherd, the Biſhop of our Souls.</q> 
               <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:50742:37"/>
            <head>Advertiſement of BOOKS Printed for <hi>Samuel Smith</hi> at the Princes Arms in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard.</head>
            <p>THE Vanity of all Pretences for Tolleration, wherein the Late <hi>Pleas</hi> for <hi>Tolleration</hi> are fully anſwered; and the Popular Arguments drawn from the Practice of the United <hi>Netherlands</hi> are ſtated at large, and ſhewn to be weak, fallacious, and inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Book of <hi>Bertram</hi> or <hi>Ratramnus,</hi> Prieſt and Monk of <hi>Corbey,</hi> concerning the Body and Bloud of the Lord, in Latine: With a New Engliſh Tranſlation more exact than the former. Alſo an Hiſtorical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertation concerning the Author and this Work, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in both are vindicated from the Exceptions of the Writers of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Proteſtancy proved Safer than Popery, by a late Convert to the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miſcellanea in quibus Continentur praemonitio ad Lectorem de infantum Communione apud Graecos. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſio Libri de Graecae Eccleſ. ſtatu contra Object. Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Hiſt Criticae, ſuper fide &amp; Ritibus orientalium. Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis &amp; ſuccincta Narratio de Vita, ſtudiis, Geſtis, &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrio D. Cyrilli Lucarii, Patriarchae Conſtantinopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tani.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Commentatio de Hymnis matutino &amp; Veſpertino Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum. Exercitatio Theologica de Cauſis remediiſque diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diorum
<pb facs="tcp:50742:38"/>quae orbem Chriſtianum hodie affligunt. Authore</hi> Thoma Smith, <hi>Becleſ. Augl. Presbyt.</hi> 1686. Octavo.</p>
            <p>Hiſtory of the Original and Progreſs of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Revenues. By the Learned <hi>P. Simon.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>Enquiry after Happineſs, by the Author of <hi>Practical Chriſtianity.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>The Duty of Servants: containing, 1. How Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ought to breed up their Children, that they may be fit to be employed and truſted. 2. How Servants may wiſely chuſe a Service. 3. How they are to behave themſelves in it, in diſcharging their Duty towards God, their Maſter, and themſelves, with Prayers ſuited to each Duty. To which is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Diſcourſe of the Sacrament, intended chiefly for Servants. By the Author of <hi>Practical Chriſtianity. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miracles, Works above and contrary to Nature: or, an Anſwer to a late Tranſlation out of <hi>Spinoſa</hi>'s <hi>Tractatus Theolog. Politicus,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s <hi>Leviathan,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon about Frequent Communion. By Dr. <hi>Tho. Smith.</hi> Quarto.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
